<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A justification of set forms of prayer and in special of the liturgy of the Church of England; in answer to, and confutation of Vavasor Powel's Fourteen considerations, against all composed and imposed forms of prayer. By Richard Lewthwat, M.A. and rector of Wethersdale in Suffolk.</title>
            <author>Lewthwat, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1992:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A justification of set forms of prayer and in special of the liturgy of the Church of England; in answer to, and confutation of Vavasor Powel's Fourteen considerations, against all composed and imposed forms of prayer. By Richard Lewthwat, M.A. and rector of Wethersdale in Suffolk.</title>
                  <author>Lewthwat, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38], 85, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A. Godbid and J. Playford, for Robert Clavel, at the Peacock in St. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Powell, Vavasor, 1617-1670. --  Common-prayer-book no divine service --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A JUSTIFICATION OF Set FORMS of PRAYER, And in Special of the LITURGY Of the Church of England; In Anſwer to, And Confutation of <hi>Vavaſor Powel's Fourteen Conſiderations,</hi> againſt all Compoſed and Impoſed Forms of Prayer.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Lewthwat,</hi> M.A. and Rector of <hi>Wetherſdale</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Godbid</hi> and <hi>J. Playford,</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi> Lord <hi>Mowbray, &amp;c.</hi> and his Virtuous and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Counteſs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Great Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing put upon the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of <hi>Set-Forms of Prayer,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> and hearing of your Honour's reſolution, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (according thereto) of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming one in Religion, Worſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:33732:3"/>and Service of God in the way of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> with your Illuſtrious and Devout Conſort, as ye are become one by Wedlock, I thought it my bounden Duty, upon the firſt Opportunity, to make known to your Lordſhip, and your religious Lady, the great joy there is among us <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> at your coming in, as alſo to throw in my Mite and ſmall help to ſettle and continue your Lordſhip in the Religion you profeſs with us, which I can do no way better than by commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you, with our God and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, the daily reading and
<pb facs="tcp:33732:3"/>ſearching of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And as to peruſing of Books upon them, of which I may ſay with the Preacher in his prediction, namely,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes, 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>there is no end:</hi> I ſhall preſume to recommend the ſame Method my Tutor at the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity gave me, to ſettle me firm in our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, which was to be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in the <hi>Homilies</hi> of our Church, and in the <hi>39 Articles,</hi> and <hi>Rogers</hi> upon them. And withal, I beg your Lordſhip's favour, to do what I intended with all holineſs and meekneſs of
<pb facs="tcp:33732:4"/>Spirit, to have deſired of your Honourable Father, the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> (had he not gone beyond Sea) namely, to vouchſafe the reading of this ſhort Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, made publick at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of divers perſons, by him who officiated ſometimes as Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to your Honourable Family, and who is and ſhall be a truly devoted and well-wiſhing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to your Lordſhip, and your religious Conſort, and to both your renouned Relations, whileſt he ſhall be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Lewthwat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:4"/>
            <head>To my Reverend and Worthy Friend, Dr. <hi>Laurence Womock,</hi> Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Divinity, and Archdeacon of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Learned Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ACcording to my bounden Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the earneſt Deſire was in my heart to reduce as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as I could of that great number of Sciſmaticks and Separatiſts that are about us, to the Unity and Communion of our Church, among other things, in order thereto, having received the worthy Tractate of Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Conold,</hi> moſt fit to help on that my Deſign, I commended the peruſal thereof to the chief head of the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant</hi> Faction, and moſt inflexible
<pb facs="tcp:33732:5"/>heart to Reformation about us (ſo I take him to be:) for he told me then, it would be to no purpoſe, he being (as in his own expreſſion) an old grown Oak in the Principles he was in. But through much importunity, I got promiſe of him to read it over, and give me his Judgment of it, both he granted, upon condition that I ſhould anſwer to things againſt the late <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book of our Church, that were in Print, that he would ſend me. Whereupon I promiſed to give my Anſwer to the chief Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; whereby I became engaged to return an Anſwer to him of the things of greateſt concern therein; which promiſe of mine will be made good, and he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to return ſomething about that Tractate of Schiſm, if there be deliver'd to him what I have drawn up to Mr. <hi>Powel</hi>'s Fourteen Conſiderations, in the beginning of his Book; of which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, if he fail, I hope there will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of him, and of his conſtant hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and thereupon converſion of them to another Judgment and Practice. Now having made known to ſeveral perſons
<pb facs="tcp:33732:5"/>the ſaid Conſiderations, and my Anſwers thereto, as I have at times drawn them up, and my purpoſe of delivering them to the party in Writing: Divers p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns have adviſed, and deſired me to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the publiſhing of them by the Preſs, alledging withall ſeveral Reaſons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me thereto. As firſt, becauſe the Factions, ſpreading them by Copies, may willingly adulterate the Original, and ſo diſable it, as to the conviction of them they communicate it to. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if not Printed, it will not be ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly had for the benefit of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their weak Proſelytes, who are captivated, and held in the ſad bondage of the following, and like erroneous Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments and Traditions of the Jeſuitical Heads of the ſeveral Factions in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And thirdly, becauſe they hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Promiſe made long ſince, and not yet performed, he and others give out, that the Allegations in that Pamplet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Set-Forms of Prayer,</hi> cannot be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd by my ſelf, or any of my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Upon conſideration whereof, 'tis preſumed, that if my Promiſe be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb facs="tcp:33732:6"/>and publiſhed, it may occaſion the more ſecure Settlement of them in thoſe dangerous Errors; as alſo make a greater ſeduction of others to them, than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would have been.</p>
            <p>For which reaſons I have pitched upon the latter way of publication hereof (if Authority ſhall permit.) Now if your ſelf ſhall, upon peruſal, approve the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as Orthodoxal, and that it may be helpful to the bringing back but of the ſimple (yet as I preſume conſcientious) Multitude, ledd away through good Words and fair Speeches (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) of thoſe who have cauſed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Offences, contrary to ſound Doctrine. Then I moſt humbly beg, that your ſelf would Patronize this ſmall Work, being Dedicated to your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. To which requeſt, if you ſhall condeſcend, 'tis very probable, thoſe Adverſaries of our Church will not dare to rally Forces again about the preſent concerns, or to give me another chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, fearing that if ſo, you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Second upon the next Quarrel,
<pb facs="tcp:33732:6"/>whoſe ſucceſs in conflicts of this kind, they know to have been ſuch, that they will not venture upon any further Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings about this matter.</p>
            <p>But, Reverend Sir, whilſt I am arguing againſt theſe and other Errors near of kin to one another, and reading theſe Anſwers to Mr. <hi>Powel</hi>'s Errors (to ſome loth to come out of them) they tell me, I am not of the ſame Opinion as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; they ſay I was againſt <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> I now write for.</p>
            <p>Sir, to ſay a little to theſe Charges. 'Tis well known to your ſelf, by my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, word of Mouth, and Practice (but beſt known to my ſelf) that I can eaſily take upon me, by acknowledgment of my Errors and Miſtakes (for God's glory, my own and others Eternal Safety) all the ſhame, and Temporal Evils incident thereupon, which is much evident, when through your diſcovering to me the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror I was in, your ſelf knew I came as willingly, as through your help, ſafely
<pb facs="tcp:33732:7"/>down from that high and dangerous <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice</hi> I had climbed up to, of abſolute and irreſpective as well Reprobation as Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by giving too much credit to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Authors of thoſe Opinions, and by not well comparing Scriptures with Scripture touching thoſe Points. And could I think that my Grant of what they caſt upon me wrongfully, would any thing further their return to us herein, (I ſpeak it, God bearing me witneſs) I would take it all upon me, <hi>per modum altiſſimi ſilentii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sir, I have found upon Inquiſition, that both thoſe Reports have been rais'd and ſpread abroad by one not of their Judgment. The falſeneſs of that Report, that I was againſt <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> will be apparent in that I have Teſtimony under his hand that raiſed it, and malitiouſly ſpread it abroad, that at leaſt a year and a half before <hi>November</hi> the 19th, 1660. I did in my Sermon, from ſeveral places of Scripture, maintain the Lawfulneſs of <hi>Infant Baptiſm. Oportet mendacem eſſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem.</hi> And I have to the ſame Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial
<pb facs="tcp:33732:7"/>the Subſcriptions of the three chiefeſt men in <hi>Hardwick,</hi> and <hi>Pulſham St. Mary the Virgin</hi> (beſides my Accuſer.) Which Notes then deliver'd in <hi>Hardwick</hi> Pulpit, were drawn up by me in 1656. after my Living of <hi>Wighton</hi> in <hi>Norfolk</hi> was taken from me, and conferred upon Mr. <hi>Robert Hocknell.</hi> And thoſe Notes were drawn up by me at the requeſt of divers (going for <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi>) to know my Judgment about that Point, which Notes ſent them altered their thoughts, and ſtrayed their further progreſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>And whereas many ſay from the afore-ſaid Mouth, that I was againſt the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer</hi> Book I now write for;</p>
            <p>I confeſs, that for ſome ſhort time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Majeſty's Reſtauration, I omitted Officiating by the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, but did begin with the <hi>Confeſſion, Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> therein, and after the <hi>Leſſons,</hi> repeated the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and after the Prayer for his Majeſty, and other Prayers and Collects I could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat
<pb facs="tcp:33732:8"/>
               <hi>memoriter,</hi> until I might (as I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected) hear from Authority the re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning the Obſervation thereof pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually. With which Service ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the <hi>Loyal Party</hi> for a while reſted contented, but ſoon after the death of <hi>Thomas Glean,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> (a man of known Loyalty to the Crown, and Conformity to the <hi>Church of England</hi>) the Major, now Sir <hi>Peter Glean,</hi> his Son, was offended, left the Pariſh Church, in his own perſon went to <hi>Shelton,</hi> and told me ſo he would do, till I obſerved the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> as I ought to do. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon conſidering with my ſelf, that I was for ſet Forms, and had no Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt our Liturgy, and that the <hi>major</hi> part of the Pariſh was for that way, I told Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> I was reſolved if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh procured the Book, punctually to uſe it. I remember Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Expreſſion preſently was this: <hi>Coſin, I am as glad of your Reſolution, as of an Hundred Pounds given me.</hi> And the next Sunday after, according to mutual agreement, he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to me in preſence of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before any thing ſaid by me, the
<pb facs="tcp:33732:8"/>Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and deſired my Obſervation of it, which was perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by me accordingly.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, were all truth that is ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt me, I know not why the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancing me thereof ſhould allay my Proceedings herein, according to my Promiſe (though ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt alledged by them, as I judge for that end) conſidering the Charge given to St. <hi>Peter, Luke</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 32. <hi>When thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy brethren.</hi> And truly had I been againſt ſet Forms of Prayer, and our Liturgy, (as this Author was at the drawing up of theſe Conſiderations) and afterward ſhould have been convinced of the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Error, and the Damage to the Church of Chriſt, through perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance therein (as my Conſcience tells me they all are guilty of, who ſtand off from joyning with us herein) the firſt thing I ſhould have undertaken, ſhould have been to imitate St. <hi>Paul,</hi> converted to the Faith by the heavenly Viſion, who forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Preached that Faith he once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 23. I ſhould ſoon have
<pb facs="tcp:33732:9"/>endeavoured thereupon by this way I now am in, to have brought men to unite in this way of Devotion with our holy Mother, the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Thus pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to bleſs you with Health, all happineſs, and length of days, I reſt very much devoted to ſerve and honour you, whil'ſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Lewthwat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonial">
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Norf.</hi> VVE whoſe Names are here under-written, do Certifie whom it may concern, That <hi>Richard Lewthwat,</hi> Rector of <hi>Hardwick,</hi> in our ſaid County, hath, to our Perſonal Knowledge, for the ſpace of two Years, laſt paſt, been of a Peaceable, Sober, and good Converſation, hath by his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine been Inſtrumental, under God, for the increaſe of our Knowledge, and Faith in the Lord Jeſus Christ, and profitable to the Inſtruction of our Youth. And that in our hearing, at leaſt (as we compute) a year and half ſince, did in his Sermon, from ſeveral places of Scripture, maintain the Lawfulneſs of <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33732:10"/>Witneſs our Hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he doth Affirm to us, That it is yet his Judgment and Opinion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>This I Affirm from the bottom of my Heart; Witneſs my Hand;
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Lewthwat.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Gleane.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Gleane.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Sayer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Ebbettes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Subſcribed <date>this 19th day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:10"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE</head>
            <p>TO the Readers, but eſpecially to them of the ſame Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Practice with him that occaſioned the enſuing Diſcourſe, is compoſed chiefly to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance them with the great concern and neceſſity of the being of Uniformity in Doctrine and Diſcipline among them (that in the Apoſtle's ſence) name the Name of Chriſt, or that do take upon them the profeſſion of Chriſtianity. And for the evidence of the neceſſity hereof among us, I ſhall mind them firſt with that of our Saviour, in his Prayer a little before his Paſſion, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Holy Father</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>keep through thy Name thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they
<pb facs="tcp:33732:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33732:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33732:12"/>may be one, as we are. Judas</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſop, as in the 13 <hi>Chapter</hi> of this Goſpel, <hi>verſ.</hi> 39. and was gone from Chriſt and the other Diſciples to betray him, then Chriſt in his Prayer, deſires the Father to keep his Diſciples in his abſence, through his Almighty Power, in an holy Unity of Faith, Spirit and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is the ſum of theſe words, namely, <hi>that they may be one, as we are.</hi> For in theſe words Chriſt did not reſpect the ſubſtance of the Father, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in which reſpect indeed they both were one; but the conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt them (as doing, or having of things done) which was ever one and the ſame, as is evident from that of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> quoted out of the <hi>Pſalms, Hebr.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. When the Father's will is for the Son to come, the Son is as ready to come, be it from whatſoever happineſs, to whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever miſery it ſhall be. When the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be pleaſed with no typical Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices longer, but will have the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Son to take a body of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, fitted for a Peace-offering to be
<pb facs="tcp:33732:12"/>ſacrificed for the expiation of our ſins, then the Son's will is one with his, <hi>Then ſaid he, lo I come to do thy will, O God, that they may be one, as we are;</hi> One in will and conſent. And ſo the ſum of Chriſt's Prayer there was, That the Father would keep the Diſciples to be one in Faith, in Spirit, in Mind, in Judgment, in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of God, <hi>that they may be one, as we are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Chriſt did not ſee a neceſſity of this Unity to be in his Diſciples only, but ſaw it neceſſary alſo to be among all men that ſhould believe on him, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Salvation by him, as in <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20, 21. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo that ſhall believe on me through their word, that they all may be one,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brentius</hi> upon theſe words ſaith, that what Chriſt before had prayed for his Diſciples, now prays for all, that ſhould believe on him, and profeſs Salvation by him; namely, that there might be Unity among them all, in Spirit, in Mind, in Worſhip and Service of God.</p>
            <p>And now to clear up further the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Unity and Uniformity among
<pb facs="tcp:33732:13"/>Believers and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, eſpecially of them living near together: I will mind the Readers of ſome places in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Works, ſometimes praying for us, and preſſing upon us the ſame things which Chriſt pray'd the Father to keep us in.</p>
            <p>In order hereunto, I firſt urge that place of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans, chap.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>God grant ye to be like minded, &amp;c.</hi> I ſhall give but little of my own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations upon the words (the Modern Divines having ſpoken ſo fully of them, as to the preſent concern.) The words are the Apoſtles concluſion, as to what he had ſpoken from the beginning of the <hi>14th Chapter,</hi> to the Quotation, and it conſiſts of Prayer and Exhortation, each whereof do invite to the nouriſhing of Unity and Concord in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion among Chriſtian Brethren, both ſtrong and weak, upon the Apoſtles ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication there, <hi>God grant ye to be like minded, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marlorat</hi> ſays, That one of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Expoſitors upon the words ſaith to this purpoſe, That the Apoſtle there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb facs="tcp:33732:13"/>both with God and the Church, withal profeſſing Chriſtianity to be of one and the ſame judgment, and mind (as to the way of God's Worſhip) which, ſaith the Author there, is the very <hi>eſſe</hi> and being of Chriſtian Charity, and where that effect is not, 'tis impoſſible there ſhould be true Chriſtians, or any Salvation: for that all true Faith is there extinct, and the fear of God is not among them.</p>
            <p>The later words of the Author are underſtood of Diſſenters from the true Churches of Chriſt, which be where the Separatiſts live: namely ſuch Churches as ours of <hi>England</hi> is; which is invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible by any authentick Arguments of <hi>Romiſh, Presbyterian, Independant, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtical</hi> Factions, or of any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; our Church being like that in <hi>Sion,</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Pſalm</hi> the <hi>48th, verſ.</hi> 12, 13. fortified with all the Impregnable Towers and Bulwarks of the Doctrines, Seals and Diſcipline of the Goſpel of Peace and Salvation.</p>
            <p>Which Church of ours was by many of the late <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independant</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33732:14"/>Separations acknowledged to be Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxal, and that they had no ſuch Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, but that they could joyn with us in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God, as well as others of their judgment formerly, now did, and a long time before had done: and this was (to my knowledge) the loud, frequent, and publick Expreſſion of many of them, long before the laſt Sea-Engagement with the <hi>Dutch;</hi> but yet many of them thus owning conviction, ſaid, They thought it not fit to own ſo much by conforming at that preſent juncture of time, upon this inſufficient reaſon alledged by them; Becauſe, that if they did as then conform, they ſhould lie under the ſcandal of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, out of fear, conſidering the ſmart and ſevere Execution of the Penal Statutes in many parts of the Kingdom, upon the Direction and Charges of the Judges in their Circuits. Which acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Conviction of many of them, and reaſon of Non-conforming alledged for that preſent, is thought by loyal and and charitable Hearts, ſounded in his Majeſty's Ears, and was the main end
<pb facs="tcp:33732:14"/>of his ſuſpenſion of the Penal Statutes for a while, by grant of the Tolleration; namely, that they might thereupon take the opportunity to conform without the forementioned Scandal. For his Majeſty there ſaid, That ſeeing the forementioned harſher Means would not prevail, he would try what that gentle way of Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration for the preſent might do for their return to us: I am ſure his Majeſty's words were to this purpoſe. Of which opportunity ſome made preſent uſe, to my knowledge; for the Sunday after the Tolleration came down to <hi>Norwich,</hi> ſome came then to both <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> and <hi>Sermon,</hi> and not before, (I Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at St. <hi>Stevens</hi>) and ſo have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſince, as I have had information upon inquiry. <hi>C. G. C.</hi> Which Practice of ſome was the hope or deſire of his Majeſty for all, which is evident from the other reaſon alledged by his Majeſty, for granting the Tolleration, which was, That whilſt he had Wars abroad, he might have Peace at home; whereupon loyal and charitable hearts cannot but judge, that notwithſtanding the Tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb facs="tcp:33732:15"/>his Majeſty therein did publiſh his diſlike of the Separations, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly check Nonconformity: and poſſibly might inſinuate a jealouſie of the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> from the Eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that it might be in their hearts (if they had but Opportunity, Power and Advantages, as formerly) to Rebel forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with againſt his Majeſty, and to Involve again this Church and State in blood and confuſion.</p>
            <p>And now I beg pardon for this ſhort Digreſſion from the laſt quoted Text, (becauſe not paſſing by without throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Mite into the Treaſury erected for the relief of Uniformity in Religion, which ſtands now in as much need in this Kingdom for help, as ever) I come with one Gloſs more upon the Apoſtle's forementioned words, which I hope ſhall be prevalent with Diſſenters from us, for their return of ſome to us, and for the unity of others with us, it being as apt and genuine an Expoſition of Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> (a man ever of great Eſteem with them) as ever he gave of any Scripture, ſpeaking of thoſe words of the Apoſtle;
<pb facs="tcp:33732:15"/>namely, <hi>That with one mind and one mouth ye may glorifie God,</hi> &amp;c. And upon the words immediately going before, he ſaith, <hi>Ac quo magis commendabilem,</hi> &amp;c. <q>that the Apoſtle might render their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement and Unity the more commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, the Apoſtle teacheth how neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Unity in Worſhip is, ſeeing God is not truly worſhipped of us, unleſs all our minds and tongues agree together in praiſing and glorifying of him.</q> The ſum of his Inference thereupon is, <hi>Non eſt ergo quod jactet quiſquam,</hi> &amp;c. <q>Let no man therefore boaſt or think he hath well worſhipped or ſerved God, doing it his own way;</q> That is, ſeparating in Worſhip from, and not joyning therein with the true Church of Chriſt, by him at the times appointed for Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and Devotion. <hi>Tantum enim Deo,</hi> &amp;c. <q>For ſo pleaſing to God is the Unity of his Servants therein, that he will not have his Glory ſounded forth in ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and injuſtifiable Debates and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords about the manner of his Worſhip and Service. In Congregations and Churches with them &amp; by them,</q> where
<pb facs="tcp:33732:16"/>he is called upon and ſerved, according to, or not againſt his Rule in his Word; as our Church of <hi>England</hi> in all things punctually obſerveth. For which addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Gloſs of mine upon Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s laſt words I have the Apoſtle backing of me, <hi>Romans</hi> 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Mark them that cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them, for they that are ſuch, ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Author makes ſo good an uſe and application of the Apoſtle's ſupplication there, that were it generally practiſed by the Factions among us, the glory of God would be ſo magnified, the Church of Chriſt here in <hi>England</hi> ſo comforted and augmented, the State and Kingdom ſo ſettled and united, and thereupon ſo ſtrengthned, that then <hi>England</hi> would be in the eyes of Chriſt her husband, as his Eſpouſe was in the <hi>Canticles, chap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 4. namely, <hi>Beautiful as</hi> Tirzah, <hi>and comely as</hi> Hieruſalem; and would be to <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other her deadly Enemies, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as an Army with Banners. His uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inference follows in theſe words:
<pb facs="tcp:33732:16"/>
               <hi>Hac una cogitatio,</hi> &amp;c. <q>The thought where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of alone may be ſufficient to reſtrain that mad and outragious behaviour of contending and ſcoulding (without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence given (he means) about matters of Religion) which as yet doth poſſeſs too much the heads of multitudes.</q> I tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it <hi>ſcoulding,</hi> 'tis ſo like the debates of froward Women, being commonly carryed on ignorantly, by meer paſſion and ſpiritual pride; not by Scripture, Reaſon, Authentick or Church Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. For as to the later, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>If any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch Cuſtom, nor the Churches of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to help all men among us, to be as careful and ſtudious, to be quiet, and to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace hereafter, as it hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n their labour and glory to be diſquiet, and to break it, I'le remembrance ye with one thing more recorded of Mr. <hi>Calvan.</hi> When Dr. <hi>Cranmer,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rogers <hi>upon the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 Articles, <hi>in his</hi> Preſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the Infancy of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches (being
<pb facs="tcp:33732:17"/>in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth) was taking care for that one mainly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary thing of Uniformity in Doctrine and Diſcipline among the ſaid Churches: To effect that bleſſed Work, he imparted his thoughts to ſeveral perſons of rareſt note throughout <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> underſtanding the Archbiſhop's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, addreſt his Letters to him, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd his ſervice thereto, ſaying, That might his Labours ſtand the Church in ſtead, <hi>Ne decem quidem maria,</hi> &amp;c. <q>It would not grieve him to Sail over ten Seas, to give his help to ſuch a bleſſed Undertaking.</q> The which if he had done, and had given aſſent and conſent to the Labours of the Reverend, Learned, and Modeſt Divines of our Church, it might happily have prevented his dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and doubtful Determinations about Election and Reprobation, depoſited in his Inſtitutions; or if they had been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed before, might perhaps have been retracted by him, to the laying aſide the long and fruitleſs diſturbance of the Churches of Chriſt thereupon. And now drawing towards an end, I ſhall mind ye
<pb facs="tcp:33732:17"/>with the Argument our Saviour uſeth in his Prayer, to keep all Believers in the before-mentioned Unity; He prays <hi>the Father, they may be all one,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That the World may believe that thou haſt ſent me.</hi> Here our Saviour mentions the great help of Unity and Concord among men profeſſing Chriſtianity, to bring the World, that is (as I may rightlier gloſs upon the word <hi>World</hi> there, than they that tie it up to a peculiar number of the Elect) multitudes of people to the Faith of Chriſt. For indeed Unity among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians will do by the World, ſometimes doubting of the Chriſt, or <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as Chriſt's Miracles did for <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> it will ſettle them ſo far in the Faith, as to own, <hi>That this is he that ſhould come, and that they will not look for another.</hi> So our Saviour Chriſt expreſly ſpeaking of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, under the Notion of Mutual Love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Diſciples, or of both together, <hi>John</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have Love one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now ſee the fruit or benefit of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Uniformity in a Church of
<pb facs="tcp:33732:18"/>Chriſt, and among men profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; 'tis the great means, under God, to add to the Church of Chriſt daily ſuch as may or would be ſaved, and to bring the World to know and believe, that Chriſt is the ſtone ſet at naught by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> builders, and is become the head of the corner; and that there is no Salvation in any other, and that there is no other name under heaven given, whereby men muſt be ſaved, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.11, 12.</p>
            <p>And as Unity in the Church is thus helpful to bring in them that are without and Unbelievers, to the ſaving Faith of Chriſt, ſo Difference and Diviſions there do keep men without from coming in, that were entering, which is evident from the rule of contrary cauſes, which is to produce contrary effects, which I could evidence from Examples, if it were not for fear of being too tedious in ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent truth. And upon this conſideration to bring back again, and to reunite to us them that are ſeparated and gone out from us, I deſire them to conſult and mind the ſad ſtate and condition Chriſt and his Spirit ſay they are in. In the
<pb facs="tcp:33732:18"/>life to come, inſtead of their ſeat they might had with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> it muſt be with <hi>Scribes, Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</hi> See <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.13. and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now hint to you in a Breviate what might be ſhewed further to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ye to a return, and come into the Society and Fellowſhip of our holy Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God is not with ye, for God is the God of Love, Peace and Unity, where he is truly and rightly worſhipped, (as he is in our <hi>Church of England</hi>) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſeparating from it, in ſuch groundleſs, heady, fierce, and fiery ſtorms, as ye have done, God is no more in you, nor with you, nor them, than he was in the ſtrong winds, Earth-quake, and are, that made ſuch noiſe and havock upon the Mount <hi>Horch,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. where 'tis ſaid, <hi>God was in none of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, God by his word hath ſilenced ye and ſuſpended ye from
<pb facs="tcp:33732:19"/>your uſurped Office, for that in the 50 <hi>Pſalm, verſ.</hi> 16. is againſt ye, <hi>Why doeſt thou preach my Laws, and takeſt my Covenant into thy mouth, whereas thou hateſt to be reformed, and haſt caſt my words behind thee.</hi> For <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>Thou ſatteſt and ſpakeſt againſt thy brother, and haſt ſtandred thine own mother's ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place, God's Spirit denys ye to be Churches of Chriſt, or elſe at leaſt he charges ye with ſuch evil Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms as none of them have, or at leaſt as they ought not to have; for thoſe words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 16. belong to you, and to ſuch as you are. If any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtome, neither the Churches of God. The Factions do not only ſeem contentious, they have too deeply engaged themſelves therein, for either their own or others ſpiritual good.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, Ye are by the Apoſtle deliver'd, with the inceſtuous perſon, up to Satan. As I may ſay, he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated
<pb facs="tcp:33732:19"/>you, <hi>Romans</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Mark them that cauſe diviſions and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces contrary to the doctrine ye have learned, and avoid them.</hi> If ye will be holding forth the Word, as ye call it, the Apoſtle would have ye have no other Auditors than the Walls and Stools are with ye; he orders all to avoid ye, none to hear ye, or aſſociate with ye, unleſs for your converſion.</p>
            <p>And now, from my Heart, for your converſion to us, in the Apoſtle's words to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the <hi>1ſt Epiſtle, chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>I do exhort ye, and beſeech ye, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, That ye all ſpeak the ſame thing: that there be no diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together with us, in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And to prevail with ye all to joyn with us ſpeedily in Worſhipping the God of Peace and Unity, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ye in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Philippians</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>If there be therefore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of
<pb facs="tcp:33732:20"/>the ſpirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, have the ſame love, being of one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, of one mind with us. Let nothing henceforth be done through ſtrife, or vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, but in lowlineſs of mind, let each eſteem other, better than themſelves.</hi> So biddeth farewel to ye all,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Lewthwat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:33732:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>February</hi> 26. 1677.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Lewthwat,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <hi>Have heard, read, and conſider'd of your</hi> Treatiſe, <hi>Intituled,</hi> A Juſtification of ſet Forms of Prayer, and in eſpecial of the Liturgy of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in Anſwer to, and Confutation of <hi>Vavaſor Powel</hi>'s Fourteen Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations againſt Compoſed, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Forms, <hi>&amp;c. And upon the whole matter I conceive it may be very Uſeful and Profitable, eſpecially to the vulgar ſort of ſeduced</hi> Diſſenters, <hi>to with-draw them from their former Errors, and procure their Return to
<pb facs="tcp:33732:21"/>the Way of</hi> Divine Worſhip <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the</hi> Church of England, <hi>if you will be perſwaded to permit it to be made Publick by the Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Nerford, <hi>B. D. Rector of</hi> Attleburgh, Norf.</signed>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I</hi> Edward Atkinſon, <hi>Rector of</hi> Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, Norf. <hi>deſire the ſame thing.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33732:21"/>
            <head>To the Compoſers, Impoſers, Readers, and Hearers of <hi>COMMON-PRAYER,</hi> to the Diſputers and Writers for <hi>COMMON-PRAYER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Would deſire ye all in the Name and Fear of the All-ſeeing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and All judging God, to ſet theſe following and the like Conſiderations to your Hearts, and your Hearts to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> How jealous the Lord of Heaven and Earth is, of his own Worſhip and of all the Parts and Circumſtances thereto belonging. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How abominable and unacceptable, to this holy juſt God, have been, and is, all Idolatrous Superſtitious and Falſe Services, and all that do ſerve him, in any way or thing, which he hath not himſelf commanded and appointed. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.25,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33732:22"/>26. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.22. and the 66.3, 4. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 9.13, 14. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 20.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How ſorely and ſeverely hath he puniſhed thoſe Kings, Prieſts, Prophets, and people, that have been falſe Worſhippers, and ſwerved from his holy Commandments. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.6. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.34.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider whether God doth call upon any of you all, to offer him any ſuch Service as this is, and whether he may not ſay to you, as he did once to <hi>Judah; Who hath required this at your hand? Iſai.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. How inconſiſtant with the day and light of the Goſpel, is this Service, God having ſent his Word more fully and plainly to direct his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and People, and given his Spirit in a more abundant meaſure, to help and enable them to call upon him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. How little good (if any at all) hath been done by the long uſe of the Service-Book, though men have prayed long by it, that the reſt of their lives might be holy and righteous, and yet they ſtill continue profane and unrighteous.</p>
            <p n="7">7. How much hurt it hath done, in ſholdering and thruſting out many godly, painful, ſoul-ſaving Preachers, and in bringing in and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſo many ignorant, ſcandalous, lazy, and formal Prieſts and Curats, to the deceiving and utter undoing of precious ſouls.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether the impoſing of the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy (which in ſome things was better, though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33732:22"/>in ſome others was worſe than the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) was not the beginning, and the firſt cauſe of the late grievous Wars, and if ſo, whether men ſhould not be more cautious to do the like for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether if the truth were throughly and truly weighed and examined, the firſt end of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Common-Prayer-Book (which do's ſo much ſymbolize with the Maſs) was not to bring Papiſts to Church, but it effected ſo little therein (not becauſe they ſo much diſliked it, as becauſe it was not in <hi>Latin,</hi> and commanded by the Pope) that it rather confirm'd them in their Maſs-ſervice.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether ſome may not intend by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing this Book, to oppoſe and put down that excellent and gracions Spirit of Prayer and Preaching, which God hath poured out upon his Miniſters, and to make this a ſnare and net againſt all Preachers and people that out of Conſcience cannot conform thereto.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether any perſons can produce any ſuch Liturgy or Form of Prayer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World, either among the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Geztiles,</hi> till above three hundred years after Chriſt, when Anti-Chriſt began to exerciſe Papal Power.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether if there were no other reaſon, but that this Book hath been ſo much Idoliz'd by the generality of men, and offenſive to ſo many Chriſtians, it ſhould not be done with as the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33732:23"/>Braſen Serpent was by <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether one end of Chriſt's coming into, and one part of his work in the World, was not to redeem men from the Rudiments and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, of which this is one; And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not a ſin againſt the Blood, and Spirit, and Goſpel of Chriſt, to impoſe, maintain, and continue ſtill the uſe of the ſame. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10, 11.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Whether at the great and terrible day of Judgment any Magiſtrates, and Miniſters, or People can juſtifie before Chriſt the making, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, reading, or hearing of this or the like Service? And whether good men, as far as they build with this Material, will not ſuffer loſs? And whether thoſe can ſtand then in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without fear, ſhame, and ſorrow, that have caſt out, perſecuted, impriſoned, or otherwiſe afflicted the true Preachers, and Servants of God, who did chooſe to obey God rather than men; And to obſerve his Divine Will, rather than the Traditions of men? <hi>Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give thee</hi> (you) <hi>underſtanding in all things.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.7. <hi>I eſteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate every falſe way.</hi> Pſalm 119.128.</p>
            <p>With theſe fourteen Conſiderations <hi>Vavaſor Powel</hi> begins his Invectives againſt Liturgies, ſet-Forms of Prayer, and Common-Prayer Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was Printed at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Livewell Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Anno</hi> 1661, and was deliver'd to me, to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33732:23"/>peruſe, and to give my judgment thereof, the fore-mention'd part whereof, I have conſider'd, and according to promiſe do return ſome of my thoughts upon theſe conſiderations, in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words;</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Oppoſers, Contemners, and Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecters of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and to the Diſputers and Writers againſt <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Would deſire you all in the Name and Fear of the All-ſeeing, All-mighty, and All-judging God, to ſet theſe following Propoſitions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to your Hearts, and your Hearts to them, being evidently enough, though ſecretly cloſed and couched in the wombs of the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Conſiderations.</p>
               <p>But before I come to open the Contents of the Conſiderations (which I preſume are framed eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for a Scare-crow to the Worſhippers and Servers of God, in the Way of our Church of <hi>England</hi> by the Book of Common-Prayer, and by a Compoſed Form, or Forms of Prayer, by the Miniſters before their Sermons) I deſire all that admire the reaſons laid down againſt this kind of Worſhip, to conſider, that the Author doth not intend only the Condemnation of our Common-Prayers, but of any Common-Prayer whatever hath been Compoſed, or ſhall be; for he writes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33732:24"/>to the Diſputers, and Writers for Common-Prayer; and to the Compoſers, Impoſers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of Common-Praver, which terms are indefinite, and are equipollent in Logic to Univerſality, ſo that the Author is againſt all Common-Prayer, whatever have been, or ſhall be Compoſed, or Impoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that you may ſee by the Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſucceeding diſcourſe, there is no leſs then a condemnation, by the Author, of <hi>David,</hi> of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> of all the ancient and modern Churches, and Divines, yea and of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, that came into the World to ſeek and to ſave that was loſt.</p>
               <p>And now to ſhew ye the blindneſs of this Guide, Diſputing and Writing againſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer, and the danger of them that follow him, and ſuch as are of his erroneous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> I deſire ye to ſearch the Scriptures, as concerning this matter, where we find Records, that Common-Prayers, and ſet-Forms have been Compoſed, Impoſed, and Uſed by them that were ſanctified, yea, by them that had Authority from Heaven, to inſtruct and guide men in the Worſhip and Service of God. In the 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. verſ. 7. <hi>Then on that day David delivered firſt this Pſalm, to thank the Lord, into the hand of Aſaph, and his brethren;</hi> if ye look upon what follows, ye have the form of the Thankſgiving: If ye look before that <hi>7th</hi> Verſe, ye ſhall ſee the occaſion thereof; and the Quire appointed to ſing it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33732:24"/>unto the Lord in the Ears of the Congregation.</p>
               <p>But come we to look into the Goſpel; and that in the <hi>11th</hi> of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> at Verſe the firſt, our Saviour's Diſciples deſired him to teach them to pray, <hi>as John alſo taught his Diſciples;</hi> hereupon Chriſt compoſed a Prayer, the Form being, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. yea, and impoſed it upon them, to be uſed by them: <hi>when ye pray, ſay, Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Now this Prayer was, and is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer; 'tis a Prayer belongs to every one of Chriſt's Diſciples, becauſe it ſutes all their occaſions, and 'tis commanded, That they uſe it as oft as they pray; <hi>When ye pray, ſay, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. but yet not ſo injoined that they ſhould uſe no other when they pray; but that as good Expoſitors give the meaning (as is the practice of the beſt Reformed Churches) and men of the ſoundeſt judgments, they ſhould either at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or ending, or in ſome part of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, ſend up the deſires of their hearts to God in that form of Prayer; And if upon theſe Conſiderations, that Prayer be not Common, or a ſet-Form of Prayer, I know not what is meant by the notions of Common or ſet-Form of Prayer. King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of moſt bleſſed memory, in his Contemplations upon the Ordinance againſt the Common-Prayer-Book, ſaith of this our Lord's Prayer, that it is the warrant, and original pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of ſet-Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p>Further, conſidering Chriſt's Diſciples requeſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33732:25"/>there, 'tis more then probable, that <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> had Compoſed a ſet-Form of Prayer to be uſed by his Diſciples in their Devotions and Service of God.</p>
               <p>One Precedent more I ſhall mind ye of, for juſtification, for Compoſing and Uſing ſet-Forms of Prayer in the Churches of Chriſt, which I bring from the practice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Epiſtles, to the ſeveral Churches of Chriſt. St. <hi>Paul</hi> knowing, as he ſaith, in the 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> Chap. 3. Verſe 6, 7. That 'tis not of his planting, nor of <hi>Apollo</hi>'s watering by the word alone, that Grace is begotten, or increaſed in men, but that 'tis by God's bleſſing the word thereto: doubtleſs hereupon it was that he ever began his Epiſtles, with prayer to God, for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual bleſſings to be to them, through the word he ſent them.</p>
               <p>And if ye peruſe the beginning of his Epiſtles, he being to bring down the ſame bleſſings upon the ſeveral Churches from God by his Epiſtles and Prayer to God, he uſeth ever the ſame ſet-Form of Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. Verſ. 7. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. Verſ. 2. his Prayer for them is in the ſame form of words, <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace be to you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> See St. <hi>Paul</hi> having the ſame mercies of Grace and Peace, to ſeek at God's hand, to be power'd down upon thoſe Churches, by his Epiſtles to them, his heart aſcends up in deſire to God, for their ſpiritual benefit thereby in the ſame words.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33732:25"/>
               <p>Nay, and 'tis not a Common-Prayer, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy for himſelf only to pray by, but for others alſo, for himſelf, and <hi>Soſthenes,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> Verſ. 2. for himſelf and <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Corin.</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 2. and <hi>Philip.</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 1, 2. and <hi>Coloſ.</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 1, 2.</p>
               <p>Yea, 'tis a ſet-Form for himſelf, <hi>Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus,</hi> Epiſt. 1. <hi>Theſsal.</hi> 1. Verſ 1, and 2. <hi>Theſsal.</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 1, 2. Yea further, 'Tis a ſet-Form for himſelf, and the Brethren with him at <hi>Rome,</hi> praying to God through the means of that Epiſtle for the re-eſtabliſhing the <hi>Galatians</hi> in the Goſpel from which they were fallen, 'tis the Prayer for them all, <hi>Grace be to ye, and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Galat.</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>So that the ſumm of this alledged out of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s practice to juſtifie ſet-Forms of Prayer (whoſe Deſire and Prayer to God for <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, <hi>That they might be ſaved,</hi> as <hi>Romans</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi> Verſ. 1.) amounts to this, That St. <hi>Paul, Soſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes, Silvanus, Timotheus,</hi> and the brethren with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> did put up their Prayers to God, for his beſtowing ſpiritual bleſſings upon the ſeveral Churches of Chriſt, through the word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ace, did put them up. I ſay, in a Common-Prayer, in a ſet-compoſed (or, as the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts call it) ſtinted Form of Prayer; And conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the afore-mentioned Chriſtians and Saints continued ſo long in a Common ſet-Form of Prayer for thoſe Churches, I cannot think but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33732:26"/>the pride, ignorance, heady, and high-minded Spirits of theſe men (had they lived in days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) would have charged St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt that joined with him in Devotion for the Churches with what they caſt upon the painful, orthodoxal, conformable Clergy of our Church in the ſeventh Conſideration, where they call them Ignorant, Scandalous, Lazy, and Formal Prieſts, and Miniſters, to the deceiving and utter undoing of precious ſouls, and ſhould they have had but ſuch Revenues, Salaries, Tithes, and Gleabs gone along with their Labours, as our reverend Biſhops, Deans and Chapters, and ſome of our Clergy had with theirs, their Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Uniformity in Prayer, eſpecially it being ſo ſhort (how holy ſoever their lives had been) was crime enough for their Houſes to have been Plunder'd, their Eſtates Sequeſtred, and their Perſons Impriſoned.</p>
               <p>And now to leave off the further confirmation of this unjuſtly condemned Practice of Devotion, by the uſe of ſet-Forms of Prayer in the times of the Old and New Teſtaments, and in the times of the Antient Churches before Popery, and in the days of the Reformed Churches, fallen from the Pope, I ſhall only commend to your conſideration, the Prayer of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we even cloſe our dayly Devotions, as in all probability he, and the people he was over, did conclude their Worſhip of God, in their ſet-Forms of Prayer.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33732:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almighty God who haſt given us Grace at this time with one accord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I confeſs 'tis not the Forms of Prayer, be they never ſo Admirable, as to Expreſſions, without the fervent deſires of the Heart, be the man never ſo righteous that utters them, that do avail ought with God; but when a man from the ground of the heart aſcends up to God in Forms, be they never ſo antient, ſhort, or Common, (provided they be lawful as to the Matter, and laudable as to the manner of the Expreſſion) ſupplicating, praying, interceding, and giving of thanks; then they become at the Throne of Grace, ſuch as St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>5th</hi> of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> Verſ. 8. ſaw in Heaven, when the 24 Elders fell down before the Lamb, namely, <hi>barps, and golden vials full of odours, even the prayer, of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hereupon was the exellency of <hi>David</hi>'s Prayer, of which he ſpeaks, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Verſ. 58. <hi>I made my petition with my whole heart.</hi> There are recorded in the Scripture divers Forms of Prayers and Thankſgivings, Compoſed by <hi>David,</hi> and other devout Worſhippers of God; queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for the uſe of themſelves and others: in the frequent Commemorations of God's Mercies to them, and for their Supplications to be made unto God, their wants being again the ſame or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like as formerly. But now that which made theſe Forms of Prayer effectual, <hi>David</hi> mentions in the ſame place, where he ſaith he did it with his whole heart. All the powers and faculties
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33732:27"/>of his Soul were now acting in their ſeveral places, ſo as he might prevail with God to ſupply his wants. And a devout ſoul, ſetting dilligently to this, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Twelve reſolved to do. <hi>Acts</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> Verſ. 4. namely, give themſelves much to prayer, as <hi>David</hi> did, namely petition the Lord with his whole heart, let it be in a ſet-Form, that that praying ſoul goes to God, that ſoul cannot want ſucceſs long. For if the Spirit it ſelf, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Romans</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> Verſ. 26. be not yet helping his Infirmities; it will not be long before he be with him, making Interceſſions for him: <hi>i. e.</hi> working in him gronings that cannot be uttered, nor long unanſwered by his God, if the things petitioned may be conſiſtant with God's glory, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners true good; and what hinders that this ſoul praying to, or praiſing God in a Form as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore limited, may not be accepted of God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God hath his whole demand of him in a way not inhibited by him, as is evident, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. Verſ. 26. <hi>My ſon give me thy heart.</hi> So that what St. <hi>James</hi> ſaid of faith without works, and of faith with works, may be ſaid of Common, or ſet-Forms of Prayer without the heart going up to God with them, and with the heart going up to God in or by them. In the 17 Verſe of the ſecond Chapter, he ſaith, that <hi>faith if it hath not works, is dead being alone;</hi> and in Verſe the <hi>26th, as the body without the ſpirit is dead, ſo faith without works is dead alſo;</hi> faith with out works, is like the body
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33732:27"/>without the ſpirit; it acts nothing to the good thereof. Even ſo the beſt Forms of Common-Prayer, if there be wanting in the man that utters or uſes them, a ſpirit or heart of ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they prevail nothing with God for him; they may be Vials, but they are without Odours or Incenſe, and ſo no ſweet ſavour to God. But then in the 22 Verſ. the Apoſtle, that faith by works was made perfect: and in the 23 Verſ. that by virtue thereof faith was imputed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for righteouſneſs, and he was called the friend of God. Even ſo Common Forms for Prayer by fervent earneſt ſupplicating hearts, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God in them, the Common Prayers, but as dead in themſelves, are thereby made perfect, yea lively; and the praying man thereby is own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and dealt by as his friend.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now end my reaſoning for the lawful and juſtifiable uſe of Common Forms of Prayer, that ſuit our wants, our hearts being in a praying condition, with the practice of our Saviour in his bitter Agonies; <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. Verſ. 39, and 42. there is mention of Chriſt's praying to the father, for the Cup to paſs from him; and having no grant, and reſolving to ſeek God further for it, in the 44 Verſ. 'tis ſaid, he went away again, and prayed the third time, ſaving the ſame words.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, To prevail with ye, to come off from the dangerous Frrour ye are in, as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent, I ſhall mind ye with the Reaſons King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of moſt bleſſed memory,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33732:28"/>hath laid down for the preſent purpoſe, in his Obſervations upon the Ordinance againſt the Book of Common-Prayer.</p>
               <p>I will write down ſome Paragraphs in that Tractate, that they that have not his Book, may read the Judgment of that bleſſed Martyr, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matter now in hand.</p>
               <p>In the ſixth Paragraph his Words are theſe: <q>For the manner of uſing ſet and preſcribed Forms, there is no doubt, that wholſome words, being known and fitted to mens underſtandings, are ſooneſt received into their hearts, and apteſt to excite, and carry along with them judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and fervent affections.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In the eighth Paragraph thus he writes: <q>I could never fee any reaſon, why any Chriſtian ſhould abhor or be forbidden to uſe the ſame Forms of Prayer, ſince he prays to the ſame God, believes in the ſame Saviour, profeſſeth the ſame Truth, reads the ſame Scriptures, hath the ſame Duties upon him, and feels the ſame dayly wants for the moſt part both inward and outward, which are common to the whole Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In the ninth Paragraph he goes on thus; <q>Sure we may as well before hand know what we pray, as to whom we pray, and in what words, as to what ſenſe; when we deſire the ſame things, what hinders we may not uſe the ſame words? our appetite and digeſtion too may be good when we uſe, as we pray for, our dayly bread.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33732:28"/>
               <p>I will write down here the thirteenth Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, which though it juſtifies Common Forms of Prayer, yet condemns not, but rather approves what our Adverſary ſo magnifies (as to down with ſet-Forms of Prayer) provided it be done with a religious and prudential care.</p>
               <p>His words follow:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Though I am not againſt modeſt, diſcreet, and humble uſe of Miniſters Gifts in publick, the better to fit and excite their own and the peoples affections to the preſent occaſions; yet I know no neceſſity, why private and ſingle abilities ſhould quite juſtle out, and deprive the Church of the joynt Abilities, and concurrent Gifts of many learned and godly men, ſuch as the Compoſers of the Service-Book were, who may in all reaſon be thought to have more Gifts and Graces, inabling them to Compoſe with ſerious deliberations and concurrent advice ſuch Forms of Prayers as may beſt fit the Churches common wants, inform the hearers underſtandings, and ſtir up that fiduciary and fervent application of their Spirits (wherein conſiſts the very life and ſoul of Prayer) then any private man by his ſolitary abilities can be preſumed to have with what they are many times (even there, where they make a great noiſe and ſhew) the affectations, emptineſs, impertinencies, rudeneſs, confuſions, flatneſs, obſcurity, vain and ridiculous repetitions, the ſenſleſs, and oft-times blaſphemous Expreſſions,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33732:29"/>all theſe burthen'd with a moſt tedious and intolerable length, do ſufficiently convince all men, but thoſe who glory in that phariſaick way.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And the ſaid King <hi>Charles,</hi> having in the <hi>15th</hi> Paragraph ſhewed the neceſſity of the uſe of Forms, of publick Compoſure in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Sacramental Adminiſtrations, and the like in the <hi>16th</hi> Paragraph; his words are as follow:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>A ſerious ſenſe of which Inconvenience in the Church inavoidably following every mans ſeveral manner of Officiating, no doubt, firſt occaſioned the Wiſdom and Piety of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Churches, to remedy thoſe Miſchiefs, by the uſe of conſtant Liturgies of Common Compoſure.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And now for a cloſe (at preſent) as to my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations upon the preſent ſubject of Common-Prayer, what can ſolidly or commendably be ſaid againſt the Uſe of Set and Compoſed Forms of Prayer, to put up to God the ſervent deſires of our hearts by. If the ſaid Forms be lawful, lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and convenient as to the Matter and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ſuiting together with our wants: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we have ſuch a cloud of Authentick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors for it, as <hi>David, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Saviour, St. <hi>Paul, John the Baptiſt,</hi> beſides the Fathers, the Antient Churches, the devout and pious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Divines, yea, and I might have recounted even all late Reformed Churches, till theſe late
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33732:29"/>upſtart, anti-Chriſtian, heady, high-minded, late Factions aroſe, diſturbing the Unity and bleſſed Peace of our, and other true Churches of Chriſt, denying the Lord that bought them, and without Repentance; bringing upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Proſelytes ſwift deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And now I ſhall end my Meditations, as to what preceded the Author's propoſed fourteen, Conſiderations, (following now to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of) in the very Words of the before quoted King <hi>Charles</hi> of Bleſſed Memory, with which he ends his Obſervations upon the ſaid Ordinance againſt the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wiſh (ſaith he) their Repentance may be their only Puniſhment; that ſeeing the miſcheif the diſuſe of publick Liturgies hath already produced, they may reſtore that Credit, Uſe and Reverence to them, which by the Antient Churches, were given to Set Forms of ſound and wholeſome Words.</p>
               <p>And now having ſhewed the groundleſs Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of the Author, to Common and Set Forms of Prayer (given me to peruſe) and to give my opinion concerning the aforeſaid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and having alſo, from the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and otherwiſe, juſtified the Uſe, and manifeſted the Aptneſs of <hi>Common-Prayers,</hi> for our Devotions, Worſhip and Service, to be put up and performed to God. I now come to ſpeak to the Fourteen Conſiderations, which the Author propoſeth to the World as unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33732:30"/>Evidences (in his judgement) to make the aforeſaid kind of Worſhip and Service, (though never ſo Conſcientiouſly, Sincerely, and Heartity performed) to be damnable, becauſe abominable to God, and not required of us by him, as is to be collected out of his four firſt Conſiderations.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore now ſpend a little time about the ſaid Conſiderations, and look into the Bowels of them, (they being in the whole, like the great Horſe framed at the Seige of <hi>Troy</hi>) in the Body whereof, were incloſed men enough to deliver up the City to Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>For in this Fabrick and Womb of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, are incloſed concluſions and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons enough to deliver up treacherouſly, the City of God, the Souls Redeemed by Chriſt's Blood, to Hell, and its Aſſiſtants, the Beſeigers thereof, to Eternal Deſtruction, (if impenitent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed, and perſevered therein.)</p>
               <p>I will therefore open the Door of this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (compoſed by deceitful Workers) having transformed themſelves in the Apoſtle's ſence, into the Miniſters of Chriſt: And letting out the deadly Enemies therein, the falſe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſhall ſlay them with the two edged Sword of God's Word and known Truth; That they make no further devaſtation hereabout, upon them for whom Chriſt dyed.</p>
               <p>In he Conſiderations, the Author falls from the way he beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in, as to the quantity of a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33732:30"/>propoſition, namely, the univerſality of his condemnation of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> in his Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite term; for now he endeavours, eſpecially to keep the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book of our Church of <hi>England,</hi> from a glorious Reſurrection; which had been Crucified, Dead and Buried ſo long time by the long Parliament and their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For all his Magazine is ſpent in killing again, what they thought they had killed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for ever, namely the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book.</p>
               <p>In the four firſt Conſiderations are contained four poſitive Concluſions, which the Author endeavours to make good by Scripture, and thereby to overthrow the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book of our Church; for which purpoſe, even the whole part of the following Pamphlet is ſpent.</p>
               <p>Look upon the firſt Conſideration beginning thus; How Jealous the Lord of Heaven and Earth is of his own Worſhip, and of all the parts and circumſtances thereto belonging: <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and withall look upon the latter part of the ſecond Conſideration, at theſe words, All that do ſerve him in any way or thing, which he hath not himſelf comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or appointed. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ye ſhall ſee thus much to be imply'd and inſerred. <hi>The Propoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord, in the Scriptures hath ſet forth his own Worſhip and Service for us to perform and obſerve, as to all the parts, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33732:31"/>way and things thereto belonging.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parts, Circumſtances, any way,</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> are his own words, as ye may read in the firſt and ſecond Conſiderations, and are ſecretly affirmed there by the Author, of the Worſhip and Service of God, to the ſame purpoſe I have predicated them in the Propoſition.</p>
               <p>To which I thus Anſwer;</p>
               <p>As to the eſſential and abſolutely neceſſary parts of our Worſhipping and Serving God, or as to what is to be believed and morally done by us to be ſaved; I do grant, they are contained and ſet forth; firſt fully in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and that by <hi>Moſes,</hi> from the Mouth of God; though not ſo cleerly as ſince, becauſe of the Vail that was over; ſo that then they could not ſteadfaſtly ſee to the end of them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>And they are again fully ſet forth in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and that by Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, from the Father. <hi>John</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 50. <hi>Whatſoever I ſpeak therefore, even as the father ſaid unto me, ſo I ſpeak.</hi> Whereupon Chriſt is called the <hi>Word; John</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. that is, the Word of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; becauſe, as the Father taught him ſo he ſpake. <hi>John</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. Therefore in reſpect to the ſetting forth fully the Worſhip and Service of God, and way to Salvation, as to the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts thereof; both Chriſt and <hi>Moſes</hi> have approbation, by the Author to the <hi>Hebrews, cap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>Conſider the Apoſtle and high
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33732:31"/>Prieſt of our profeſſion, Chriſt Jeſus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> faithful to him that appointed him, as alſo</hi> Moſes <hi>was faithful in all his houſe</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to grant that the Worſhip and Service of God, ſet forth ſo ſufficiently by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or Chriſt, as before granted, was directed and order'd, as to all the circumſtances, words, ways and things by them, or any under them, is to grant more than can be proved by the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>For to inſtance in one particular, eſſential part or duty of Worſhip or Service, we ſee, that when God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or his Son, or by any under them, have commanded men to call upon God, by Prayer, in time of need; or to praiſe him for his goodneſs to them; all the Circumſtances of this Duty, as to words, or forms, or places, or number of times of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, or Praiſing of him, are not fully ſet forth by them, neither by Precept, nor Example; for we ſee the Examples herein diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſering: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 164. the Pſalmiſt is at his Devotion ſeven times a day; and <hi>Daniel</hi> is but three times; <hi>Daniel</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. And ſo as to the Poſture or Geſture in performance of the Duty, have not been the ſame; <hi>Daniel</hi>'s poſture was kneeling, in the place aforeſaid. <hi>Luke</hi> 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. the <hi>Publican</hi>'s was ſtanding. <hi>Deut.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Moſes</hi>'s poſture was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falling down upon his Face at his Prayers; And as much may be ſhewed, as to other Duties.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33732:32"/>So that from this hath been ſaid, 'tis evident, the circumſtances, wayes, and things, (as the Author calls them) as to the Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, were not all commanded and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, in the Author's ſence.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I cannot ſee, but that our Church Liturgies are more juſtifiable than either the ſet Forms of the factious Perſons, (which ſome of them deſire ſhould not ſeem to be ſet Forms, by reaſon of their diſuſe of them, for ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time) yea, and more juſtifiable than their Extemporary Prayers, (which they falſely and blaſphemouſly call, Praying by the Spirit:) Conſidering, that both in their Compoſed Forms, and Extemporary Prayers, for the moſt part (if not always) they <hi>conſent not to wholſome Words, even the Words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nor to the Doctrin which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Godlineſs,</hi> to uſe the Apoſtle's Phraſe, in the firſt to <hi>Timothy, cap.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. with nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which can they charge our former, or preſent <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book.</p>
               <p>Look upon the former part of the ſecond Conſideration, which begins thus; How abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and unacceptable to this holy, juſt God, have been all Idolatrous, ſuperſtitious and falſe Services.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition is this, as the Author's opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All Idolatrous, Superſtitious, and falſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices are abominable, and unacceptable to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33732:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This Propoſition, I grant to be a Truth; for God wills us to own him to be God, yea and him alone, 2 <hi>Kings, cap.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the Land,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other gods, but me.</hi> As to godſhip, lordſhip, and abſolute Supremacy, God will indure no Corival in the heart of Man. And whoſoever aſcribes to any Creature, what the Scriptures have peculiarly attributed to God, is guilty of Idolatry and Superſtition alſo.</p>
               <p>All therefore that is to be faulted in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, is the Author's miſapplication of the Propoſition; for he applies it to them that worſhip God devoutly, and call upon him fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently, in a juſtifiable Form of Prayer. And I ſee not, but the Author, in ſo applying the forementioned Propoſition (iſſuing out of that conſideration) how he can be guilty of leſs than Blaſphemy, in terming that Service of ours Idolatrous, ſeeing we worſhip the true God rightly.</p>
               <p>Where is our Idolatry, or falſe Service, in that Worſhip and Invocation? Is it in our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God by Prayer in time of need, through the only Mediator betwixt God and Man, Chriſt Jeſus, our Saviour? As we do, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing with our Mouths, becauſe, believing with our hearts, that God is both able and willing to ſupply our wants, as is neceſſary to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33732:33"/>be in devout ſouls, in order to obtain at God's hands: <hi>Hebrews</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. In all this, I hope, we are neither Idolatrous, nor falſe in our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. The Author might rightly have applied to himſelf and his Proſelytes the Doctrin or Propoſition, conſidering his words in the ſeventh Conſideration, where he terms their own Speakers, Soul-ſaving Teachers; for in ſo ſaying, he is both Idolatrous and Superſtitious, in aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing that to themſelves, which is the peculiar of the infinite Wiſe God. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>I, even I, am the Lord, and beſide me there is no Saviour.</hi> Is he not therein Idolatrous and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, in aſcribing to their own Teachers, to be both the Fountain and Cunduit-pipe of Salvation, or ſaving Grace, as there he doth? If not ſo, I am ſure he falls thereupon, under St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s reprehenſion of the carnal and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Factions, in the 1 <hi>Corimh. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. For indeed it will be evident, when I come to ſpeak of the aforeſaid conſideration; that that have been and are but ſuch as our Saviour ſaid, the Scribe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Phariſees, and Hypocrites were: <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 <hi>ver.</hi> 13. where he ſaid, they did <hi>Shut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, did neither go in themſelves, nor ſuffer them that were entering to go in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before I paſs from the Conſideration and Propoſition, I muſt touch a little upon the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part thereof, which is alſo by the Author, miſapply'd to our Liturgy, and them that uſe it.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33732:33"/>
               <p>He looks upon our Worſhipping of God in that form, to be a falſe Service; and the chief places he brings to diſcover what a falſe Service is, are <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66. <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4. and <hi>Jerem. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14. where the Prophets give the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why God had no reſpect to <hi>Iſraels</hi> offerings, and why he gave up the Land to periſh, and to be burnt; and it was, they ſay, becauſe the People had forſaken God's Laws, and followed their own ways, and their own abominations. Now all this makes nothing againſt our Liturgy, or the Worſhippers of God by it; for our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book hath nothing in it againſt the Will of God, or his Worſhip, ſet forth in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>I conclude therefore, that had the Author applied the falſe Service he there ſpake of, and the recited places, out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> to himſelf and the reſt of the Factious, as to their Worſhip and Service, he had done right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for I am ſure that their Service, both as to Prayer and Inſtruction, in moſt things, was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what they falſely charge upon us, namely, a falſe Service.</p>
               <p>As to their Prayers, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of moſt Bleſſed memory, hath evidenced the falſeneſs of their Service, ſeeing God by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 Epiſt. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2. exhorts, That Prayers and Supplications ſhould be made for Kings, and all in Authority. For in the laſt Paragraph but one, in his Obſervations
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33732:34"/>upon the Ordinance againſt the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book: His words follow thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>One of the greateſt faults ſome men found with the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, I believe was this, that it taught them to pray ſo oft for me; to which Petitions, they had not Loyalty enough to ſay, <hi>Amen:</hi> Nor, yet Charity enough to forbear reproaches, and even Curſings of me in their own Forms, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Praying for me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Look upon the third Conſideration, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>How ſorely and ſeverely hath he puniſhed thoſe Kings, Prieſts, Prophets, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that have been falſe Worſhippers, and ſwerved from his holy Commandments, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.6. <hi>Num.</hi> 11.34.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Author's Propoſition, in this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is as followeth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God hath ſorely and ſeverely puniſhed thoſe Kings, Prieſts, Prophets, and People, that have been falſe Worſhippers, and ſwerved from his holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> His Proofs as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Propoſition is true, but nothing concerns them that worſhip God by the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer</hi> Book, nor are the places he quotes for Proof, againſt them that ſerve God that way: for that the Prayers of our Church are put up to the true God; we are not gone to the Abominations of this <hi>Amorites,</hi> nor to the Abominations of this Author, nor of his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33732:34"/>the Lord keep us in the Worſhip we are in, and of his Mercy bring them back to us.</p>
               <p>To the fourth Conſideration, I ſhall ſay no more, nor otherwiſe than the Author hath there ſaid to us; <hi>mutatis mutandis;</hi> Let them conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether God doth call upon any of them to offer him any ſuch Service as theirs is, and hath been? And whether he may not ſay to them for their ſo doing, as they have done, as he did once to <hi>Judah?</hi> Who hath required this at your hands? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p>Look into the fifth Conſideration, being this:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>How inconſiſtent with the Day and Light of the Goſpel is this Service, God having ſent his Word more fully and plainly to direct his Miniſters and People, and given his Spirit in a more abundant meaſure, to help and enable them to call upon him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Conſideration, in the beginning of it (conſidering what in the beginning of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the Author writes to the <hi>Compoſers, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, &amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi>) contains mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly in the Author's opinion this following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition as a truth.</p>
               <p>To make uſe of ſet Forms of Prayer in the time of the Day and Light of the Goſpel, to put up the deſires of our Hearts to God by, is no way juſtificable. 'Tis plainly his opinion, for he ſaith, that this kind of Service is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33732:35"/>with the Day and Light of the Goſpel. And the following part of his Conſideration is in manner of a reaſon to confirm it; for he ſaith, that in the Day and Light of the Goſpel, God hath ſent his Word more fully and plainly to direct his Miniſters and People, and given his Spirit in a more abundant meaſure, to help and enable them to call upon him, than by that way of <hi>Common,</hi> or <hi>Set Forms of Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the beginning of my Confutation of this Author, in my juſtifying ſet Forms of Prayer, (as there limited) and that from the practice of our Saviour in his drawing up, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſe of his ſet Form. As alſo from the practice of <hi>David,</hi> of St. <hi>Paul, Timothy,</hi> and others, I have ſufficiently overthrown this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and his Argument and Reaſon alſo brought for confirmation of it, conſidering that it was the time and day of the fulleſt Light and Promulgation of the Goſpel, and of God's en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling Men by his Spirit to call upon him, that ever was ſince; in which was the juſtification of ſet Forms of Prayer, after, by the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Examples and Precedents.</p>
               <p>Well, but yet for further Anſwer, let en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry be made, what time the Author here means by the Day and Light of the Goſpel, in which he ſays, the Spirit was given in a more abundant meaſure to help, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For ſatisfaction herein; It was not meant of the time of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, David, Chriſt, John Baptiſt,</hi> or the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33732:35"/>for, as hath been ſhewed, ſet Forms were conſiſtent with thoſe Days of Light, and help of the Spirit to call upon God.</p>
               <p>'Tis certain therefore, that by theſe words in his conſideration, namely, the Day and Light of the Goſpel, the Author means the times of the late Wars, and horrid Rebellion, the times he wrote and inveighed againſt the beſt ſet Form for publick Worſhip and Service of God, that ever was extant before it, namely the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, before this.</p>
               <p>And now as for a fuller Anſwer, I grant, that with thoſe their Days of Light, (which was as great a darkneſs as ever was ſince Chriſt, as to Spiritual things) the Glorious Liturgy of our Church was inconſiſtent, being a Worſhip and Service according to God's and Chriſt's Rule and Doctrine; for that the practice of the Oppoſers of the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book was diametrically oppoſite to the Day and Light of the Goſpel of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and therefore could have no more Concord together, than St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> could have, which was none at all; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was notable policy (though nothing of true Religion) of the Counſil of <hi>Belial,</hi> (to uſe His Majeſty's expreſſion) to Crucifie the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book by an Ordinance; for had the Liturgy of our Church and their <hi>Belial,</hi> their Army, ſtood together, it would have been, ſoon as it was with <hi>Dagon,</hi> when the Ark of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33732:36"/>God and it ſtood together, which ſoon fell down and brake in pieces; their Army would ſoon have moulter'd to nothing; what a confuſion and conſternation would have been among them, and upon them; had that Book or the ſubſtance of it either been in uſe by their Miniſters, as by the expreſs word of God is commanded ſhould have been? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3. What thoughts of heart would have been in thoſe rebellious ſpirits, when being ſent up to fight againſt his Majeſty, and his Forces, before they had gone to Battel, they muſt have prayed to God to be the preſerver of him and them they were going to deſtroy; for ſo 'tis in the Litany, according to the Command of God, <hi>that it may pleaſe thee to be the King's defender, and keeper, and to give him victory over all his Enemies;</hi> and in the Prayer for him, 'tis, <hi>ſtrengthen him that he may vanquiſh and overcome all his enemies.</hi> So that had they continued our Liturgy as was their duty to have done or had their Prayers been according to God's direction in his Word, they muſt (as much as in them lay) have been by Prayer bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſtrengthning his Majeſty, and curſing and weakning themſelves in their Enterpriſes, by preceding Supplications for both.</p>
               <p>To end therefore my Anſwer as to this in general; I confeſs indeed the former Common-Prayer-Book, and almoſt all Prayers, according to God's revealed will in his Word, yea and all found Scripture Doctrine, were inconſiſtent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33732:36"/>with the times of the day and light of the Goſpel by the Author's calculation: but in the light of the Goſpel in the times of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, they were conſiſtent and juſtifiable; for they had then no contradiction nor diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement by God in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> nor by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the <hi>New,</hi> as is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved at the beginning of my Tractate. This may be ſufficient to that fifth Conſideration, if not, go on as followeth.</p>
               <p>But to give the Adverſary the faireſt play that may be, and to ſave him and his aſſiſtants the labour of replication, perhaps they will plead their more abundant help of the Spirit, to call upon God than formerly, from their mode, or manner of praying; and that in three reſpects. Firſt in reſpect to the length of their Prayers: or Secondly in reſpect to their Extemporary, and Unpremeditated way of praying. Or Thirdly in reſpect to their more powerful, and argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative way they uſe in their Prayers, to prevail with God for the things they ask.</p>
               <p>I will briefly conſider what may be ſaid for them, and what againſt them, as to the before-mentioned reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, They will ſay 'tis evident they are much more inabled by the Spirit to call upon God than formerly, conſidering the length of their Prayers.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer.</p>
               <p>This is of no moment to them that will be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33732:37"/>guided by the Precedents and Precepts in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, as to this mode of praying: For, firſt, the practice of the Saints and holy men of God have in the weightieſt matters and concerns been ſhort in their Prayers put up to God; <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Interceſſion for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for deſtruction, was but ſhort. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, 24, <hi>&amp;c. Jacob</hi> in his great fear, that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould deſtroy him and his, going to God by prayer for ſafety, his Prayer is paſt over in four ſhort Verſes, with all the Arguments he uſed to prevail with God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay Chriſt himſelf, ſeeking by prayer for the Cup of Death to paſs from him, his Prayer was ſhort every time in his Addreſs to the Father. <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. <hi>verſ.</hi> 39, 42. <hi>Father, if it be poſſible, let this Cup paſs from me; nevertheleſs not as I will, but as thou wilt:</hi> his Prayer was as ſhort the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time; and the third time it was no longer than at firſt, for it was the ſame.</p>
               <p>The Precepts of God and his Spirit are againſt this mode of long Prayers, and therefore no argument from the length of their Prayers, that they are more inabled by his Spirit to call upon God. See for this, 1 <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 5.1, 2. as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning hearing, when men come at the Houſe of God, he would have them very attentive: as to the length of their Prayers, he orders them to be ſhort, God is in Heaven, and thou upon Earth, therefore let thy words be few.</p>
               <p>And our Saviour in his Sermon upon the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33732:37"/>Mount, directing how to Pray effectually, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as well concerning the length of Prayer, as to the matter thereof. <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>When ye pray, uſe not vain repetitions as the heathen do;</hi> the Original is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: which is tranſlated, <hi>ne inania loquaemtra,</hi> which our Church renders very well, <hi>uſe not vain repetitions;</hi> where our Saviour forbids tautological words, variety of Expreſſions to one and the ſame purpoſe. Learned <hi>Sharp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in his <hi>Symphonia Propheta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um &amp; Apoſtolorum,</hi> ſaith, That the word there uſed by our Saviour, is taken from one <hi>Battus,</hi> a ſooliſh Poet in thoſe days, whoſe Verſes were tedious, to a loathing, by means of many divers and vain words to the ſame ſignification. So that there our Saviour admoniſhed his Diſciples and all men, that their Prayers be not nauſcous, through tediouſneſs, or multiplicity of words, which is abliorred of God and devout ſouls. <hi>Voſ.</hi> 9. <hi>praedicti Capitis; after this manner pray ye:</hi> that is in a conciſe and ſhort manner.</p>
               <p>Further, If in reſpect to the length of their Prayers, they or their hearers will conclude their more abundant help of the Spirit to call upon God, they do deny the Nature and being of God and Chriſt, as deſcribed in the Scriptures; for <hi>James</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>With God is no variable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſe, nor ſhadow of change.</hi> And <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever.</hi> Now if it be through the help and direction of the Spirit, that their Prayers
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33732:38"/>are ſo conſtantly long, over they were, by the direction of God and Chriſt, and by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Prophets, and others, inabled formerly by the Spirit, to call upon God; then it muſt follow, that with God is variableneſs, and ſhadows of change; and Chriſt is not now the ſame by his Spirit he was formerly; for if they have now help to pray, as they do, by the Spirit of Chriſt, then it follows, he is now for long Prayers; and whilſt upon Earth, by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by his Spirit in the days of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, he was altogether for ſhort Supplications. All therefore that can be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Adverſary, as to the uſual mode of long Prayers, is this, That they are carried and helped thereto, either by an heatheniſh ignorance, or by that which is far worſe, namely, by a Spirit of Vain-glory, or of Covetouſneſs, even by the ſame Spirit or ends, our Saviour ſaid was in the Scribes, Phariſees, and Hypocrites, whoſe Prayers were lengthned for a ſhew, or for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.47. and <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>But let's ſee what can be ſaid for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended more abundant help of the Spirit, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Extemporary and Unpremeditated mode of Praying.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer; If any will go thus to God in Prayer in private, but eſpecially in publick, that is, without a due premeditation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation with himſelf of the mercies received, he and the people are to be thankful for, or of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33732:38"/>the things they ſtand in need of, and are to beg of God: 'tis no leſs than unwarranted ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and raſh preſumption, in reſpect to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick and Scripture Precedents and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and to term it praying by the help of God's Spirit, 'tis no leſs than Blaſphemy in the higheſt nature. Let's look into the Scriptures for the truth hereof. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> 63. <hi>And Iſaac went out to meditate in the field:</hi> Another Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion renders it, <hi>he went out to pray.</hi> And the reaſon of theſe differing Tranſlations, <hi>Vatablus</hi> affirms to be, becauſe the word in the original, which is <hi>Suach,</hi> ſignifies both to Meditate, and to Pray; ſo that it might have been render'd, <hi>Iſaac went out to Meditate and to Pray:</hi> And then it commends thus much to our Practice, and the preſent purpoſe. Firſt, we muſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of God's goodneſs to us, and our wants; and that done, then put up our Praiſes and Prayers to God; being by that premeditation better inabled to perform that Duty than with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. A Marginal Note upon this place ſaith, <hi>That this was the Exerciſe of the godly Fathers in thoſe times, to meditate of God's merciful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſes, and then to pray for the accompliſhing of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was the practice of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 63 <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6, 7. <hi>My mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullips;</hi> look on, and you ſhall ſee <hi>David</hi> will not enter upon this Duty raſhly, without me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of God's help and goodneſs what it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33732:39"/>was; this he ſaid he would do, when he had remembred him upon his bed, and meditated on him in the night watches, becauſe he had been his help.</p>
               <p>The reſolution of the Twelve, <hi>Acts</hi> the <hi>6th, verſ.</hi> 4. will joyn in condemnation of this their mode of praying without premeditation at leaſt; there the Twelve ſaid, <hi>we will give our ſelves unto prayer continually, and to the miniſtry of the word.</hi> I preſume that by their reſolution of giving themſelves much to prayer, they neither meant a conſtant heatheniſh, nor phariſaical length of prayer, nor at all the late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> kind of unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated ſupplication (both which modes have been, and yet are too much in uſe.) No, the Twelve by giving themſelves to prayer, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the practice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the ſame Spirit with the Twelve; it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t of Compoſing Forms of Prayer for themſelves and others, to put up their Prayers by; or at leaſt of ſearching to know by meditation their own and others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they were to take care of, and then to ſeek up with <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, David,</hi> and others, inabled by the ſame Spirit of Prayer, ſuch arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, from conſideration of God's promiſes, and properties, and of Chriſt's undertakings, and from conſiderations of mens wants, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, that thereby they might put up to God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> effectual and ſervent Prayers for themſelves, and thoſe they were ſetover by Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33732:39"/>
               <p>Which gloſs may very well be admitted, as the meaning of the twelve Apoſtles there, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s direction, concerning Prayer, who was of the ſame dedication with the twelve, both as to Prayer, and the Miniſtry of the Word.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3. the Apoſtle there, directing <hi>Timothy,</hi> and all other Miniſters of Chriſt after him, as to the manner of praying to God. He doth not there exhort to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of that duty in ſuch way as that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this or the fore mentioned mode or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, it ſhould be done according to God's will. His Exhortation is not, that men pray for Kings and all in Authority. The Original is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort that Prayers be made,</hi> which word bears, to be compoſed, prepared, or made ready, as in a form up to God, to put the deſires of their hearts for all men, for Kings and all in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that we may lead a peaceable and quiet life, in all godlineſs and honeſty. 'Tis confeſt, that in the Apoſtles times, among other miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous gifts of the holy Ghoſt, ſome had their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Effuſions. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14, 15. and with the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, <hi>Every one of you hath a Pſalm,</hi> &amp;c. but the Apoſtle obſerving that this beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſo much Emulation, Faction, and confuſion among them, he reſtrained the uſe of thoſe Gifts, and injoyned, that all things ſhould be done decently, and to that effect that they ſhould be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33732:40"/>done <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, according to rule, appointment, and order, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. and the <hi>40th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or again, the former gloſs upon the reſolution of the twelve Apoſtles, of giving themſelves much to Prayer, may be admitted as their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, conſidering what it was for them to give themſelves to the Miniſtry of the Word; for what is meant of giving themſelves to the word, is meant of giving themſelves to Prayer. Now the Apoſtles by giving themſelves to the Miniſtry of the Word, was meant their ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the will of God, their ſtudying, and meditating of the mind of Chriſt, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, Scripture with Scripture, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting one with another of the ſure way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; as we ſee was their practice when the difference aroſe about Circumciſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to the <hi>30th.</hi> Which thing is alſo evident from the practice of the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe giving himſelf to the Miniſtry of the Word, was doing what he commended in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. namely, labouring in the Word and Doctrine, by ſtudy and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word of God, joyned to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God's ſpirit, that was helping of him. So that I ſee not, but that that place where the twelve Apoſtles reſolved to give themſelves much to Prayer, rightly expounded, gives a ſuffrage with the practice of <hi>Iſaac, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and others, in condemning this mode of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33732:40"/>unpremeditated praying to God; And ſo I ſhall end my declamation againſt it, with part of the ſecond Verſe of the fifth Chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes;</hi> (the end whereof before, with other places of Scripture, gave ſentence againſt the heatheniſh and phariſaical mode of Prayer) <hi>Be not raſh with your mouths, and let not your hearts be haſty, henceforth, to utter any thing before God, for God is in heaven, and you upon earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But though I have ſaid thus much againſt the two former modes of Prayer, as they be uſed by the factious, againſt both Scripture Precedents, and Rules for Devotion; yet I would have the Adverſaries know, that I am not ſo againſt ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and unpremeditated Prayers, or long Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, either as that God's people ſhould never uſe them; there is ſometimes occaſion for both, and a time when neither is to be neglected; for a ſudden Prayer we have warrant for, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to, from the practice and preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Diſciples. <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.25. When upon a ſudden ſtorm the ſhip was ready to ſink, and they to periſh, they run to Chriſt with, <hi>Lord ſave us, we periſh.</hi> And there is occaſion ſometimes for long Prayers, as there was in the time of God's provocation, by the ſins of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> when it was the Lord's reſolution to have deſtroi'd them; <hi>Deut.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18, 19. then <hi>Moſes</hi> is at Prayer forty days and forty nights. Which is alſo upon extraordinary occaſions, the practice of our Church; for in the times of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33732:41"/>God's heavy Judgments upon the Land, or upon ſome particular place theref, the ſure Evidences of God's diſpleaſure becauſe of our ſins, then our Church appoints days of Humiliation, and the Prayers to God upon thoſe days are length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then, as well as fitted to the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Which is alſo ordinarily the practice of our Church; it being our duty from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s churge, ſometimes to remember in our Prayers all Men, Kings, and all in Authority: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on our Church lengthens our Prayers at times by the Litany, and ſo, that 'tis hard to find where the concern of any one man is neglected; yea, and ſo well 'tis compoſed alſo as to brevity, fulneſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the diſpatch of the Duty injoyned, that I heard our late Biſhop <hi>Reynolds</hi> (where judgment was of high eſteem with them of the Author's faction, if they did not diſſemble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> give it this <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>comium:</hi> That it was the moſt excellent compoſed Prayer that ever was uſed in the Worſhip of God, ſince the times of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſaid, He was of opinion, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Divines then living ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> join <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in making another, they couldl not parallel it.</p>
               <p>But let's look now upon the third reſpect, their lat City of refuge, as to the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, which is their more ſpiritual, powerful, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mentative way to be uſed in Prayer, to prevail with God. In which reſpect, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e they challenge to themſelves a more
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33732:41"/>abundant help of the Spirit, as to Prayer, than others, yea than thoſe that compoſed this Form of Common Prayer for the Church and themſelves to ſeek God by.</p>
               <p>Well, now as to the trval hereof, we muſt to the Orale, or Word of God, and conſider of the Precedents and Directions therein, as to the way of powerfulneſs and prevalency with God by Prayer, and ſee whoſe Pravers, the Churches or theirs, be beſt ſitted to help the ſouls of people to a fiduciary, ſervent, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual way of praying to God, or which be moſt ſutable to Scripture Directions herein.</p>
               <p>And as to lead to this, we need go no further than to our bleſſed Saviour, helping his Church in their Devotions and Pravers. <hi>mait.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>After this manner therefore pray ye; Our Father which art in heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. The ſpirit of Chriſt tells us, that without Faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God in the performance of any Duty, and there concludes, that he that goes to God by Prayer effectually, he muſt believe that God is both able and willing to relieve them that diligently ſeek him, that is the ſumm of that place.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſt, as helping devont ſouls to obtain at God's hands the things they ſtood in need of by Prayer; directs them in the beginning, to the minding of that may raiſe and continue in the praying foul, a faith or belief in God, in order to a diligent ſeeking of God, ſo as he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33732:42"/>may obtain. <hi>Our Father which art in heaven,</hi> for there he remembers them, with the power of God to help, in that he tells them God is in heaven, to whom they pray, and therefore above the reach of earthly things to hinder his will: he alſo there minds them, that he is as willing to relieve, as able, in remembrancing them he is their Father. And in the cloſe of his Direction, he teacheth them to argue even undeniably with God, to grant their requeſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>thine is the kingdom, the power and the glory;</hi> here are ſtrong Arguments to incline a God of power, of truth, of juſtice, of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and of greatneſs as God is, to vouchſafe the things he directed his Church to ask, and whereof they ſtand in need. For there he teacheth his Church to remembrance God, that he doth no wrong to any in granting their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired neceſſities, they mind him he hath right to diſpoſe of where he pleaſe the things they begged. Secondly, they mind him, 'tis in his power to grant their deſires.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, in the cloſe of all, they mind God of his own advantage upon the grant of their requeſts, yea and enter into a Covenant alſo, to be for ever thankful to God upon his granting their requeſts: all theſe are couched together in that cloſe, commonly called by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines the <hi>Doxology,</hi> of that Prayer, <hi>for thine is the kingdom, the power and the glory, for ever and over.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33732:42"/>
               <p>And now having briefly conſidered of the direction of our Saviour, as to the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and effectual way of Prayer, let's peruſe ſome of the Prayers of our Church Liturgy, and ſome of the Prayers of them who have ſo undervalued and neglected the ſame, and let the World and themſelves judge, who come neareſt the Directory and Liturgy of our Saviour, and the practice of God's Saints in the Scriptures herein.</p>
               <p>And I'le begin with the beginning of our Liturgy, that pithy and effectual (though ſhort) Form of Confeſſion and Supplication, in order to forgiveneſs of ſins paſt, and of amendment of life for the future.</p>
               <p>As the due and fulleſt confeſſion of ſins is an infallible way, ſo alſo 'tis an only way to obtain forgiveneſs of ſins upon ſupplication thereof through Chriſt. Which we ſee in the Prodigal (being come to himſelf) and after that to his Father in the ſame way: <hi>Luke</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 21, 22. Now that devout ſouls might come up to a due performance of both, our Church fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows our Saviour's fore-mentioned Directions.</p>
               <p>It begins with <hi>Almighty and moſt merciful Father.</hi> A Procemium fitted to help every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful confitent and petitioner to faith, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance and increaſe in faith, ſo as they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with the Prodigal's hope, and deſire, to God their heavenly Father, Almighty God; and with as happy a ſucceſs as he did to his. For
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33732:43"/>here is means fit to help ſinners to go to God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> faithful hope of forgiveneſs, and conſequently to ſeek it of him diligently. For here they are briefly inſtructed, they are going to him for forgiveneſs, and for their wants, who is the moſt merciful Father in the World; nay to him whoſe compaſſion and inclination to forgiveneſs is as far beyond an earthly Father's, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are higher than the Earth: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. which thing is argued by our Saviour in <hi>Luke</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12, 13. to make men importunate and diligent ſeekers of God in Prayer. <hi>If a ſon ſhall ask bread of any of you that is a father, will be give him a ſtone? or if he ask a fiſh, will be give him a ſerpent? or if he ask him an egg, will be give him a ſcorpion.</hi> No the ſumm is this, an earthly Father will give a Child upon requeſt the things he hath need of: Ay but what follows, <hi>how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the Holy Ghoſt to them that ask him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if there be never ſo much willingneſs to help, yet if there be not ability to relieve, there will be but a ſlack and faint addreſs made, though there be never ſo much want.</p>
               <p>But now ye may ſee our Church here, after the Practice of our Saviour, hath made proviſion for the latter as well as for the former, for it aſcribes to him power to forgive all ſins, and to amend all ſinfulneſs of life in man, in attributing to him almightineſs, as well as it preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his willingneſs, in thoſe words placed before
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33732:43"/>the Confeſſion and Supplication, <hi>Almighty and moſt merciful Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Exod. 32. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 31.</note> And in the cloſe of this Confeſſion and Prayer the Church follows Chriſt there, and the Saints of God cloſe.</p>
               <p>There our Church helps a devout ſoul to plead ſtrongly with God for forgiveneſs, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting grace, by way of an humble remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of God, of his PRomiſe made to Mankind, thereupon in Chriſt Jeſus. And citer that pleads with God for his help to amend their lives, that they might be inſtruments for his glory thereby.</p>
               <p>And indeed it ye look upon the Abſolution, upon the ſecond Collect at Morning Prayer, which is for Peace, upon the third, which is for Grace, upon the ſecond, at Evening-Prayer, which is for peace of Conſcience, peace with God; upon the Prayers for his Majeſty the King, for the Queen, the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and the Royal Family; for the Miniſters of the Word, and all Congregations committed to their charge, and upon moſt of the Pravers, to be uſed with the forementioned Prayers in our daily Devotions, they are fitted to awaken and help our Faith, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>erchy to ſtrengthen our wraſtling ſouls with God by Prayer, that we might overcome him, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did at <hi>Peniel,</hi> and the Lord not able to deny us bleſſings meet for us and his own glory.</p>
               <p>And now look upon ſome of the Prayers and Thankſgivings of them that have ſo diſpiſed the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33732:44"/>former, and are ſo much more inabled by the Spirit to thoſe Duties by their own Pretenſions, and ſee which have come neareſt the help of our Saviour, and the powerful, and argumentative way of the canonized Saints in the Calendar of the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>At a Market-Town in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> there being a Meeting, in order to ſetting up the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Government, the Miniſter in his Sermon, (inſtructing the Lay-Elders as to the due execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their places) told them, they muſt be as exquiſite Chirurgeons, who have Hauks eyes, Ladies hands, and Lions hearts.</p>
               <p>But one of that Faction, taking on him to pray a Bleſſing upon the work of the day, among other things, he deſired God he would give the Lay-Elders, Hauks eyes, Ladies hands, and Lions paws.</p>
               <p>That I ſhall not omit of one in his Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Sermon, in his Thankſgivings, bleſſed God for the twelve Biſhops being ſent to the Tower, in the long and mad Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that thereupon God had ſet Chriſt Jeſus twelve ſteps higher in his Throne than ever he was before.</p>
               <p>Another Miniſter, being to Preach a Funeral Sermon at another Miniſter's Pariſh, he that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiated before the Sermon, read the <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> where, in the <hi>4th Verſe,</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power, and who can ſay to him, what doeſt thou?</hi> The Miniſter
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33732:44"/>that was to Preach (being for the preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion) fearing the people (in all probability) might have been brought to, or continued in Loyalty, upon the remembrance of <hi>Solomen</hi>'s Doctrine, uſed this poiſonous Antidote, in his Prayer before the Sermon. <hi>O Lord, though</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>hath ſaid, that Kings cannot be controuled, yet we thy people know by the Spirit, that Kings may be queſtioned and call'd to account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will inſert but one more Expreſſion in Prayer, which was lately told me, by one that heard it, being preſent himſelf at a Church in <hi>Suffolk:</hi> in the Prayer of a Miniſter in great eſteem, in thoſe days. After ſome Groanings and ſmall coughing Reſpits, theſe words came forth: <hi>Lord go on with thy Reformation, while it is time:</hi> (and after ſome more coughing Reſpits, he went on thus) <hi>For if thou doſt not, thou wilt not know what to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that theſe and ſuch like ridiculous and profane Expreſſions, and dead argumentative helps were too frequently uſed in the Prayers of thoſe ſo boldly aſſuming to themſelves a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative, or extraordinary help of the Spirit to call upon God, are in common charity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability to be received as truth, (even by thoſe that have not heard them, or the like to them) conſidering the report, as to ſuch like particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, left to be publiſhed by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of moſt bleſſed memory, being then in his own thoughts, but a few ſteps from the grave.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33732:45"/>For in his Obſervations upon the Ordinance againſt the Book of Common-Prayer, in the twelfth Paragraph there, having ſtigmatized many of their Prayers with ſtatneſs, rudeneſs, confuſion, ridiculous repetitions, yea with ſenſleſs and oft-times blaſphemous Expreſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the thirteenth Paragraph, he concludes to my preſent purpoſe, in theſe following words; <hi>Wherein they muſt be ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>ly impudent, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers of themſelves, not to have an infinite ſhame of what they ſo do, and ſay, in things of ſo ſacred a nature, before God and the Church, after ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and indeed prophane a manner.</hi> But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what hath been laſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, I cannot but grant, that ſome of them, infatuated with the ſame ſpiritual pride, and ſelf conceitedneſs, have been more prudent, and careful than others, in compoſing and wording their Publick Prayers; but yet if they be weighed in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des, and with the Weights of the Sanctuary, with the Collects and Prayers of our Liturgy, ſo deſpiſed by them, their beſt Prayers will be found lighter than the other, in the judgment of meek, humble, and devout ſouls, knowing how to pray as they ought, through the help of the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>Look upon the ſixth Conſideration, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>How little good (if any at all) hath been done by the long uſe of the Service-Book, though men have prayed long by it, that the reſt of their lives might be holy and righteous,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33732:45"/>yet they ſtill continue profane and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Author's opinion there is thus:</p>
               <p>Thoſe men that have made never ſo long uſe of the Service-Book, and have prayed never ſo long by it to God for a ſanctified and righteous life, have never attained to any part thereof. It appears plainly to be his opinion; for poſitively and indefinitely he ſaith, though men have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long by it, that the reſt of their lives might be holy and righteous, yet they ſtill continue profane and unrighteous.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, This being the judgment and ſentence of the Author, or of any that read his Pamphlet, let them return ſpeedily with a penitent heart for and from theſe thoughts. For I ſee not but they may be ranked with the man of ſin St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, in the <hi>2d Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians, chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. who, <hi>as God, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the Temple of God, ſhewing and profeſſing himſelf that he is God.</hi> For in the <hi>Iſt</hi> of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. A Church of God, a Congregation of believers, are there called the Temple of God.</p>
               <p>Now this man, or any following this his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, living with or among a Church of God, a company of true Worſhippers of God, he or they holding and profeſſing the aforeſaid opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, are got into the Temple of God, hereby profeſſing themſelves that they are God, in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and condemning a great part of God's
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33732:46"/>Church, before Chriſt (to whom is committed all Judgment) be come in the clouds, to juſtifie ſome, and condemn others.</p>
               <p>Or if they may not be ranked there, I am ſure they may with them St <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 2 Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy, chap.</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> at the firſt <hi>verſ.</hi> and ſo on, ſaid ſhould come in the laſt and perilous times, namely blaſphemers, and deſpiſers of thoſe that are good; which evidently belongs to them, if ye do but conſider the converſations, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual comforts of the late reverend Biſhops, Deans, Prebends, and of others, outed, ſequeſtred, perſecuted, impriſoned, and murthered, both of Clergy and Laity, that were conſtant Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God, in that Form of the Service-Book in publick whilſt it could be ſo uſed, and in private afterwards.</p>
               <p>Seeing that theſe through the grace and help of God (ſerving God that way) might, and I believe did, in and from their hearts ſay in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s hope, as well as words. 2 Epiſt. to <hi>Tim. chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. namely, that they had <hi>fought a good fight,</hi> and <hi>kept the faith,</hi> and that there was laid up for them a <hi>crown of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Nay their blaſphemy and unparallelable deſpications upon this their condemnation are yet more evident, and riſe yet higher in their not excepting our late King <hi>Charles,</hi> the bleſſed Martyr. It cannot be denied, but that he was a conſtant Worſhipper of God in Publick, by the Service-Book; And prayed even to the laſt unto
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33732:46"/>God by it. Now I do poſitively ſay (and who ſhall contradict it) that there was much ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace to him from God upon his Devotion, and Worſhipping God thereby; which will be evident, if his Book Compoſed by him were but peruſed.</p>
               <p>Where ye may ſee a teſtimony of his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Comforts, and of Sanctifying Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, vouchſafed him of God, yea and of his poſſeſſion of Chriſt's and <hi>Steven</hi>'s Spirit at his approaching death, in both freely forgiving, and fervently praying for his cruel Enemies. Nor can it be thought, but that God, through the uſe of that Service-Book, did vouchſafe him help cheerfully to drink off that Cup of Death ſo imbitter'd by his Enemies; eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true report goes of his Morning-Worſhip the day before he ſuffer'd.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty being to receive the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper the Morning before his Paſſion, being the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>January;</hi> The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was to be performed by the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer, which Biſhop <hi>Juxen</hi> (then offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating) obſerved punctually, and coming to the ſecond Leſſon to be read, named it the 27 <hi>chap.</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew.</hi> At the Biſhop's naming the Leſſon, being the Hiſtory of our Saviour's Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, His Majeſty (in all probability not eying the Calender, as then it concerned him not to do) ſteps to the Biſhop, and in meekneſs asked, Why he did apply that Chapter to the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33732:47"/>The Biſhop replied to this purpoſe, and ſaid, It was the portion of Scripture that by providence was appointed for the ſecond Leſſon by the Common-Prayer Book for the Morning-Service.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid his Majeſty, <hi>Go on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that at the dreadful hour of his death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at greateſt need of help to ſuffer (as Chriſt Jeſus was, in his bloody Agonies, at the approaching of the hour of his Paſſion) God by this his appointed Leſſon for his Majeſty's Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, made the Common-Prayer Book do, for this bleſſed Martyr at that time, what the Angel did for Chriſt, when appearing to him in his Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes from Heaven, ſtrengthning him; for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by queſtionleſs God helped his Majeſty to paſs towards the gate of death, calmly, undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, and chearfully, as he did (as thouſands can yet teſtifie) nor can I ſee how it ſhould be leſs, or otherwiſe, ſeeing that God thereby gave an unexpected, and extraordinary Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to him that that day he was to ſuffer with him, even as he did, one for many, and conſequently to reign with him, and that he ſhould, this life ended, be with him in Paradiſe, ſitting with the noble Army of Martyrs, praiſing and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the God of his ſalvation.</p>
               <p>And laſt of all, to conclude againſt this moſt falſe and damnable determination of the Author, let it be conſider'd of, that God hath often given teſtimony of his acceptance of that Form of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33732:47"/>Prayer, and of the Worſhippers of him thereby, ſeeing that when God at any time hath ſhewed his Indignation againſt the ſinful people of this Land, by his ſore Judgments upon ſome places thereof; why the repenting Inhabitants, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves before this God, and ſeeking his atonement and reconciliation in this Form of Worſhip and Service, together with ſome few ſet Prayers and Portions of holy Scripture, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the preſent occaſions: why, I ſay, this Common-Prayer Book (with thoſe few apt alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) have oft-times done for <hi>England</hi> what <hi>David</hi>'s rearing an Altar at the Word of God, and offering burnt-offerings, and peace-offerings thereon, did for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam. chap.</hi> 24. <hi>ver.</hi> 25. it hath not been long before the Lord hath been intreated, and the Judgments ſtayed.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>7th</hi> Conſideration;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>How much hurt it hath done in ſhouldering and thruſting out many godly, painful, ſoul-ſaving Preachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I preſume that in this Conſideration, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath reſpect to the times before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the long Parliament, and the Wars they raiſed againſt his late Majeſty of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when according to the Law of the Land, (as now it is the ſame) the Miniſters that would not conform to the Book of Common-Prayer, could neither hold their Livings, nor Preach.</p>
               <p>In this reſpect he means the Service-Book ſhoulder'd and thruſt out many godly, painful,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33732:48"/>ſoul-ſaving Preachers, this being the ſenſe of the Author in this former part of the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as I verily believe it is) it contains this following Propoſition:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thoſe Miniſters that would not conform to the Book of Common-Prayer, were godly, painful, ſoul-ſaving Preachers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>To make which Propoſition true, the Author muſt have recourſe to ſome of their new light, for I am ſure that the old light, the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> neither by Precedents, nor Precepts therein, can they prove themſelves to be either in a godly or ſoul-ſaving way of themſelves, or of them that did adhere to their Doctrines.</p>
               <p>For ſo ſoon as his Majeſty's Grant was ratified for the two Houſes of Parliament to ſit during their pleaſure, there was ſoon a foundation for a Rebellion laid, by them and the Synod of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſitting with them. Which was no ſooner done, but thoſe Diſſenters from the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book (ſome having gone beyond Sea, and others retiring into ſecret places at home for a while) ſoon joyned all their Forces, to carry on the late moſt damnable Rebellion and Diſobedience. So that inſtead of being owned godly and ſoul-ſaving Preachers, they may juſtly be termed what the Phariſees were of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> namely an off-ſpring of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
               <p>For as 'tis the property of the off-ſpring of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33732:48"/>Vipers, to deſtroy their Dams that gave them their being, ſo did theſe forſaker, of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book</hi> ſoon help to deſtroy our moſt gracious Sovereign, that, under God, gave them their ſafe being and preſervation, as <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and for a long while deſtroyed their Mother, the true Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> which gave them their ſpiritual, ſaving, and Chriſtian light and grace, if ever they had any. So that for the juſt condemnation of the former part of the Author's <hi>7th</hi> Conſideration, what God ſaid againſt <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Hicruſalem,</hi> by <hi>Iſaiah, chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. may juſtly be applied to theſe oppoſers of the King, State, and Church of <hi>England; Hear O Heaven, and give car O Earth, for the Lord hath ſpoken, I have nouriſhed and brought up Children, and they have rebelled againſt me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſomething would be ſaid to the latter part of this <hi>7th</hi> Conſideration, where the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book</hi> lies under a great condemnation, in reſpect <hi>to bringing in, and maintaining many igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, ſcandalous, lazy, and formal Prieſts and Curats, to the deceiving and utter undoing of many precious ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which latter Paragraph, I preſume the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor had reſpect to the Times before the long Parliament, and the late unhappy Wars, and do mean thereby, that the Miniſters in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going times, which would ſubſcribe and conform to the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> (though but of mean parts) were admitted to Livings, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33732:49"/>ſuffer'd to ſerve their Cures, in which reſpect, I preſume the Author means the <hi>Service-Book brought in, and maintained many ignorant,</hi> &amp;c. as above ſaid.</p>
               <p>To which Accuſation, I make this enſuing Apologetical Anſwer.</p>
               <p>I remember that in thoſe times many of the Clergy brought into the Miniſtry in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of bleſſed memory, as alſo for ſome while after, by reaſon of a ſcarcity of Learned Men, occaſioned by the ſharp Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of ſuch Divines in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, and in another reſpect, alledged by a Biſhop at the Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court.</hi> I ſay, I remember many of thoſe Miniſters of very mean ability were then alive, and remained in their Livings. And indeed I confeſs, that in that reſpect, it may be ſaid, that the <hi>Service-Book</hi> brought in, and maintained ſome Miniſters of but mean Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; but yet were nothing ſo impudently and wickedly ignorant, as <hi>Butchers,</hi> and other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Teachers, put into publick places, after the ſaid <hi>Service-Book</hi> was crucified; for though theſe former Miniſters knew not much, yet what they knew, they knew rightly; but theſe latter, thinking they knew any thing, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth. chap.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. they knew nothing as they ought to know.</p>
               <p>In the next place the Author ſaith, this <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book did bring in, and maintain ſcandalous and lazy Prieſts and Curats:</hi> that is, firſt men
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33732:49"/>of an open wicked Coverſation. To which I Anſwer:</p>
               <p>'Tis a charge as nonſenſical as falſe, and as falſe as any thing can be. Let him ſhew where the Rubrick, or any part of the Book, yea, or any Canons, or Conſtitutions of our Church, give Toleration, or countenance of any ſuch Miniſter in that Office. If there be any ſuch ſcandalous Miniſter in the Church, the fault lies in the Officers, in not preſenting of them, not in the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> nor in them in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Authority. For as our Biſhop, when Arch-Deacon, hearing, by flying reports, of ſome ſcandalous Miniſters to be in his Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and meeting with no Informations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at his general Viſitation, he told the Officers of the reports: but withall told them, <hi>there could not be a debauched Clergy in</hi> England, <hi>unleſs there were a perjured Laity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas the Author ſaith they were lazy, that probably might be ſpoken (how dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſoever) becauſe they prated not nonſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally twice or thrice a week in the Pulpits, as ſome of their gang did uſe to do. But if the Works and Sermons of moſt of the Clergy Printed, and weekly Preached, were duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd of, both in theſe times, and in the days he complains of, in this Conſideration, they would be found generally a Clergy ſo labouring in the Word and Doctrine, as they might be thought juſtly worthy of double honour; and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33732:50"/>in that reſpect free, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> from the blood of all men, neither deceiving, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing any ſoul, as the Author uncharitably and blaſphemouſly charges here upon many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>8th</hi> Conſideration:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether the impoſing of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy (which in ſome things was better, though in ſome others worſe than the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>) was not the beginning and the firſt cauſe of the late grievous Wars; and if ſo, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men ſhould not be more cautious to do the like for the future.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I preſume that upon this Conſideration, the Author would have this believed and granted, that the Impoſing of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Liturgy, to be uſed in their Publick Worſhip and Service of God, was the beginning and the firſt juſt cauſe of the late grievous Wars.</p>
               <p>Or thus:</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Scots,</hi> and late long Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> were juſtifiable in Levying Wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſty, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and his Loyal Subjects, upon ſending, or command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or commending to them the aforeſaid Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy to be uſed in their Publick Worſhip and Service of God.</p>
               <p>One of theſe Propoſitions or Aſſertions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the meaning of the Author; in this Conſideration, in the cloſe thereof he makes uſe and application in theſe following words:</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33732:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And if ſo, whether men ſhould not be more can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c.</hi> The Propoſition being granted to be truth, whereof he would have no man doubt. He makes the Application by way of an inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Caveat, or Advice: And that is, that no Men, Kings or Church, ſhould afterwards com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, or tender the like, that is, any Liturgy or ſet Form of Prayer to the people (eſpecially of <hi>Scotland</hi>) to be uſed in the Publick Worſhip of God for the future (conſidering that Wars have been raiſed before in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> thereupon.)</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer:</p>
               <p>Conſidering the <hi>Scots</hi> received <hi>Knox</hi> his Form of Prayer, and <hi>England</hi> ever had one, I ſhall not conclude with the Author, that the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of that Liturgy was the firſt cauſe or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the late grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Wars,<note place="margin">Which I heard Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> boaſt of in St. <hi>Laurence</hi> Pulpit, the peculiar Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving day for the Defeat at <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </note> in the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Contrivers, and Managers thereof, (though it might be made uſe of, by way of occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to haſten to the Execution of their long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore contrived rebellious Deſign, and wiſhed deſire.)</p>
               <p>Nor ſhall I here enumerate or debate their pretended juſt grounds for their War. Nor ſhall I argue to evidence the unlawfulneſs of thoſe Inſurrections, otherwiſe then by remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancing men of the diſpleaſure of God with
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33732:51"/>them for thoſe their Enterpriſes, manifeſted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently in the ſucceeding events and iſſues thereof. For we ſee the Presbytery in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and their Confederates in <hi>England</hi> (the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Covenanters here) the beginners of that horrid Rebellion, ſoundly baſted, wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued (baffled, and made the laughing ſtock of the World) by the Sword of their own Party.</p>
               <p>What became of the <hi>Hothams,</hi> that ſo hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and diſabled his Majeſty of moſt bleſſed memory, to defend himſelf againſt theſe and other enemies, in ſeiſing his Garriſon, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine at <hi>Hull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as to this Topick, I ſhall deſire at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent nothing more to be had in memory, but the end of that heavy ſcourge and rod of God's Proteſtant Church, and his beloved Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> I mean the Independant and <hi>Cromwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Army, and the imparallelable High-Court of Injuſtice, the chief whereof (though the generality had mercy) died not the common death of <hi>Engliſh</hi> offenders, but that death (by the providence and juſtice of God) appointed by the Law of the Land for the worſt of Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors; and ſo let all the implacable Enemies of our Church and gracious Sovereign periſh.</p>
               <p>And now I'le have done ſpeaking to this <hi>8th</hi> Conſideration, in the ſame manner the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ended it, even by way of Application.</p>
               <p>Seeing that God brought upon that party
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33732:51"/>that raiſed Wars upon the impoſing juſtifiable and pious Liturgies (as I preſume the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> was, and am ſure the <hi>Engliſh</hi> formerly was, and this now is) ſuch a miſerable and wretched end (as the juſt wages of that rebellion) as he did upon the chief heads thereof. Let all men henceforth be ſo cautious, as not to dare to think in the leaſt of Diſobedience, or Levying Wars upon the ſame, or ſuch like grounds, as the former Rebels did, againſt this Church, and in the cloſe, our dread Sovereign, or Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>9th</hi> Conſideration:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether if the truth were throughly and truly weighed and examined, the firſt end of Compoſing the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book (which doth ſymbolize with the Maſs) <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In this Conſideration are couched divers Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of the Author, concerning the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book.</p>
               <p>One may be this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt (that is, as I preſume, the chiefeſt) end of the Author's Compoſing the</hi> Common-Prayer <hi>Book, was to bring Papiſts to Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>This is the firſt charitable Expreſſion that I have hitherto obſerved Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> to have given them that were the Authors of this kind of Worſhip, but had he made known in plain and full terms the other gracious deſigns of thoſe men thereby, as namely, to help good meaning hearts to God, by the only Mediator in Heaven,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33732:52"/>Chriſt Jeſus, (and not by Saints and Angels;) as alſo ſecondly, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs, 1 <hi>Corinth. chap.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. to help thoſe had in them a ſpirit or heart to pray, that they might perform it with underſtanding, and be able to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> effectually and ſervently.</p>
               <p>I ſay, had Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> mentioned theſe and other the gracious ends of the Compoſers of the <hi>Service-Book</hi> (God's mercies and way of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being then vailed to the generality of men, being ſet forth only in an unknown Tongue.) I ſay, he and others thereupon might have owned them to have had to the people of <hi>England</hi> the like Imployment the Angels had to the Shepherds and the World at the Birth of Chriſt, when vailed to many, by the meanneſs of his coming in the fleſh; namely this, to ſet forth by that <hi>Service-Book,</hi> the glory of God, in his peace on earth, and good will towards men, that ſo <hi>England</hi> might be in a right way to believe in Chriſt, and ſo to call upon him, that they might not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</p>
               <p>And to be ſhort, as to ſpeaking to this ninth Conſideration; what though it be granted, that it ſymbolize with the <hi>Maſs book,</hi> or that many things be in it that are in that, ſeeing there's nothing in our Liturgy but what is good, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or uſeful to Edification (as will be evident to men doubtful thereof, if they will but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe diligently Mr. <hi>Thomas Comber</hi>'s <hi>Companion to the Temple;</hi> or otherwiſe termed, <hi>A help to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33732:52"/>Devotion, in the daily uſe of the</hi> Common-Prayer: <hi>In two Parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>10th</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether ſome may not intend by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing of this Book, to oppoſe and pull down that excellent and gracious Spirit of Prayer.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As to their excellent Gifts, or helps by the Spirit, as to Prayer. And as to their godly, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſoul-ſaving Preachers, both which they have aſſumed to themſelves in the Firſt and Seventh Conſiderations, and have re-aſſumed in this Tenth Conſideration, under the notion of an excellent and gracious Spirit of Prayer and Preaching. As to their miſtake in preſuming to ſuch Gifts and Abilities, I refer the Reader hereof to what I have before written, concerning their Praying and Preaching, upon thoſe Fifth and Seventh Conſiderations. And to make a ſhort buſineſs as to ſpeak to this Tenth Conſideration, I'le give them my thoughts of the ends of re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the former Book with ſome few Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and divers Additions of ſeveral Prayers and Services, fitted to ſeveral accidental occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: The firſt whereof might be, to anſwer ſuch moderate Diſſenters (I call them ſo in compariſon of them of theſe latter days) as was Doctor <hi>Reynolds,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chadderton,</hi> and the others with them at the Conference at <hi>Hempton</hi>-Court, on the behalf of other Miniſters and themſelves, whoſe deſires (as to the Book of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33732:53"/>
                  <hi>Common-Prayer</hi>) then were, that it might be fitted to more increaſe of Piety, as our <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book now is.</p>
               <p>Another end might be, to oppoſe and pull down (as it was high time to do) the long, tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tological, heatheniſh, phariſaical, extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, nonſenſical, erroneous, damning kinds of Praying and Preaching were then, and had been too long in uſe in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third end of confirming this Book, might be, to revive and re-eſtabliſh this moſt bleſſed and excellent help for Devotion, and Worſhip of God, that ever was heretofore in the Church of Chriſt, and to countenance Orthodoxal Preachers, and ſo to maintain ſound Doctrine, which had for a long time been ſhut out of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick places for Worſhip and Inſtruction, by an uſurped Authority over this Church and State.</p>
               <p>And whereas he concludes it made as a ſnare and net againſt ſuch, as out of Conſcience could not Conform thereto; I am ſure no man can have any ground now for ſuch accuſation, or uncharitableneſs, if they do but conſider the religious care taken by his Majeſty ſoon after his Reſtauration, to anſwer the Doubts and Objections of ſuch Pretenſions, in appointing a Committee of Biſhops for that purpoſe, where and when Biſhop <hi>Reynolds</hi> had the Chair. So that indeed all that can be ſaid, as to the Book (in the intention of any of the Compoſers thereof) as concerning net or ſnare, in reſpect to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33732:53"/>Penalties made thereby to be inflicted upon the Nonconformiſts to it, they were only made againſt perverſe, obſtinate, and wilful oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the ſame, and ſo are to be clear'd from the charge of any evil intention againſt tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>11th</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether any perſon can produce any ſuch Liturgy, or Form of Prayer, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World, either among <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As to the juſtification of Liturgies, and ſet Forms of Prayer, I have ſpoken at large in the beginning of this Fractate, and ſhall therefore anſwer the Author's Queſtion in this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no otherwiſe than as our Saviour anſwer'd the Queſtion put to him in the Temple, <hi>Mark</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 29, 30. And that is by giving a Queſtion to him and his followers to anſwer, and it is this:</p>
               <p>Whether any perſons can produce any ſuch long tautological, extempory, nonſenſical Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? or any ſuch ſoul-deſtroying, damning Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins, or Sermons, ſince the beginning of the World, either among the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or any Churches of Chriſt, till this Rebellion in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> as theirs were? Let any of them anſwer me this Queſtion, and I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer further to this <hi>11th</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>12th</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether, if there were no other reaſon,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33732:54"/>but that this Book hath been ſo much idolize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the generality of men, and offenſive t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo many Chriſtians, it ſhould not be done with as the brazen Serpent was by <hi>Hezekiah</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The opinion of the Author may be ſet forth in this Propoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The generality of men have much Idolized the Book of</hi> Common-Prayer; <hi>and 'tis a juſt offence to many Chriſtians alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Author chargeth firſt a great evil to have been committed by moſt men in praying unto God, and in worſhipping of him in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Form of the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book: And that is that they have Idolized it.</p>
               <p>Now to Idolize a Creature or Thing, is taken ſeveral ways out of mentioning two of them is firſt to eſteem it as their God or Saviour. In this reſpect it may be the Author means the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men Idolized the <hi>Service-Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer.</p>
               <p>I am confident there's not a man will ſet hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart to that part of the Conſideration; for who can think men ſo ignorant, as to eſteem that their God or Chriſt to ſave them, which is that Form whereby they go to God and Chriſt their Redeemer and Mediator for forgiveneſs of ſins and ſalvation.</p>
               <p>But then ſecondly, To idolize any thing, is inordinately to ſet the heart upon it, truſting in it more than in God, and above him, in this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33732:54"/>reſpect Covetouſneſs is called Idolatry. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. Thus Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> in his <hi>Chriſtian Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thirdly, We commonly ſay, men idolize a thing, when they have a greater reſpect to, and eſteem of a thing than it deſerves. In this reſpect I preſume the Author means moſt men did idolize the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> which he thinks ſufficiently manifeſted by their ſo conſtant and frequent Worſhipping and Invocating of God thereby.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer. Conſidering the Counſel, or rather the Command of God, as to the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent performance of this Duty of Prayer, and Thankſgiving, by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18. where he bids us <hi>Pray without ceaſing,</hi> and <hi>in every thing give thanks,</hi> becauſe 'tis <hi>the will of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Conſidering that, I ſay King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, of moſt bleſſed memory, in his Obſervations upon the Ordinance againſt the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> Book, doth fully make void the Author's fore-mentioned Charge and Reaſon alledged for defence of it, in the Eighth and Ninth Paragraphs.</p>
               <p>The King's words:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>I could never ſee any reaſon, why any Chriſtian ſhould abhor, or be forbidden to uſe the ſame Form of Prayer, ſince he prays to the ſame God, believes in the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, profeſſeth the ſame truths, reads the ſame Scriptures, hath the ſame Duties upon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33732:55"/>him, and feels the ſame daily wants for the moſt part both inward and outward, which are common to the whole Church.</p>
                  <p>Sure we may as well before hand know wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> we pray, as to whom we pray, and in what words, as to what ſenſe; when we deſire the ſame things, what hinders we may not uſe the ſame words? our appetite and digeſtion too may be good, when we uſe, as we pray for, our daily bread.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Now, conſidering all this, where is any cauſe for taking away this Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> from the people, as the brazen Serpent from them of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 'tis no marvel that the Author and his Followers charge men with Idolizing this Book, in offering in Publick unto God their Prayers and Thankſgivings thereby, according to the Order and Authority of the Church, when I have heard them charge men with idolizing the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> uſing it but according to the Command of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; that is, in the ſeveral Services and Prayers of the Church, fitted and appointed to be uſed upon ſeveral occaſions before <hi>Mattens</hi> or <hi>Even ſong</hi> be over, whereof by eſpecial command of Chriſt, the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> is to be part. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. <hi>verſ</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>When I conſider the impudent Charge, I my ſelf heard from one of the Author's chief fellow Chaplains againſt ſome of the Petitions of the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> in condemning one of them in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33732:55"/>the Pulpit unlawful, as to the matter, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not fit to be uſed by moſt;<note place="margin">Hugh Peters, <hi>at</hi> Norwich, <hi>ſaid of that Petition,</hi> thy will be done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> pray for an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible thing; <hi>and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another Petition, ſaid,</hi> See what the Petitions are of that you call the <hi>Lord's Prayer.</hi>
                  </note> as alſo when I conſider the total neglect of our <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> in theſe mens Devotions, drawn up by Chriſt for a Form of Prayer, as well as for an help to compoſe our own Prayers by. I ſay, when I conſider theſe things, then what <hi>David</hi> ſaid (ſeeing the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the wicked) of his heart, I ſay of mine, namely thus, I have ſaid in my heart, that they ſay in their hearts, (though not in right down words) that Chriſt in Compoſing, and Commanding that Prayer to be ſaid as oft as men pray, is acceſſary to a very great and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral guiltineſs of Idolatry in this laſt reſpect at leaſt.</p>
               <p>Or if they ſhould not own this, yet I am ſure the total neglect of uſing it in their Devotions, prove plainly, they look upon it as a Prayer unworthy to be uſed, which is no leſs than in their hearts to blaſpheme the Saviour of the World.</p>
               <p>But then further, he ſaith the Book was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to many Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>He doth not ſay, it was offenſive to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or the weak Brethren (as is uſually the Phraſe in the Scriptures, in ſuch caſes as this
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33732:56"/>here of the Author) And that perhaps becauſe he would not have the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor the Worſhippers of God by the ſaid Book, to have the honour, to be thought to ſhare with them in the happy events of their ways.</p>
               <p>Verily I think none ſhall need to be offended at their ſecluding them from their Fellowſhip or Fraternity therein; for both <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independant,</hi> in moſt of their undertakings, were but like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in Iniquity, and at the laſt day, without repentance, muſt have the ſame doom they had from their father <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 49 <hi>verſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath, for it was cruel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, but to take it in his own terms, that it was offenſive to many Chriſtians. This term of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> was the ancient, and beſt name was given to true believers in Chriſt after his Aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: this name is, in the opinion of Divines, that St. <hi>James</hi> ſpake of, in <hi>2d chap. verſ.</hi> 7. which he ſaith was the worthy name whereby believers were called. And Divines deſcribe a Chriſtian as followeth; namely, to be one that is endowed through Grace with Faith and the holy Ghoſt, ſerving God in righteouſneſs and true holineſs all his days, as a perſon dedicated to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now if the Author ſhould produce any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian according to this deſcription (which I am confident he cannot do) or according to any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33732:56"/>hereof, congruous to the Scripture ſence, that ever was offended at the worſhipping of God in this Form of Prayer; yet there's but little ſaid to the Author's fore-mentioned pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, namely, <hi>of that Book being an offence to many Chriſtians;</hi> it being but an offence taken, where none is juſtly given.</p>
               <p>I can eaſily grant, that the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> was offenſive to ſuch Chriſtians as this Author means, and as himſelf was; and ſo was many parts of the whole Bible. In the <hi>1ſt</hi> Book of the <hi>Kings, chap.</hi> 22. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Ahab</hi> loved not to enquire of the Lord by <hi>Micaiah,</hi> becauſe he propheſied no good concerning him, but evil. And if the Author and others offended at the Book, would publiſh the reaſon thereof, from their hearts, 'tis probable, 'tis becauſe there's nothing of good for them there, but evil, being in thoſe perverſe ways. For, as I ſaid before, ſhould they have uſed that Liturgy in the time of the Wars, uſing the Forms of Prayer, they muſt as much as in them lay have been bleſſing them they were fighting againſt, and curſing themſelves, and their curſed undertakings.</p>
               <p>And truly from thoſe <hi>Leſſons, Epiſtles,</hi> and <hi>Goſpels</hi> culled out of the Scriptures, and injoined by the Liturgy to be read in our daily Service. The whole Book is but a <hi>Micaiah</hi> to them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying no good to them, but evil, for therein they muſt have found themſelves an Army fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Almighty God, to their ſudden
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33732:57"/>both preſent and eternal overthrow and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion without repentance.</p>
               <p>Now, to have done ſpeaking to the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs exceptions againſt the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book in this <hi>12th</hi> Conſideration, I have this following Opinion, That if the Author and his Party could upon the two former reaſons have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured our Church, and the Civil State of the Kingdom, to have ſerpentized the Book of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer,</hi> as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did the <hi>Nehuſhtan;</hi> they would be ſoon Scribling and Printing, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have the Scriptures (the full, ſet, and ſtinted Rule for Faith and Obedience to be taken away and deſtroyed) they having the Spirit in a more abundant meaſure than formerly (as to help to call upon God, as in Conſideration the Fifth.) So alſo to ſet up upon their Aſſertions another fuller and righter Rule for Faith and Obedience, leading to ſalvation; or elſe at leaſt to have the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Priviledge of an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purging Index, to have the Texts in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures expunged and left out in the Printed Bibles, that make for Obedience and Subjection to the higher Powers, either in Church or State; And alſo all places that command or commend Unity, Order, Peace or Conformity in or to the Churches of Chriſt, and whatſoever in the Bible make againſt their Opinions and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices.</p>
               <p>Which Opinion of mine may be looked upon as charitable, or true, conſidering, among other
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33732:57"/>things of that kind (I could inſtance and prove) was acted at <hi>Much-H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>um</hi> Church in <hi>Hartford</hi>-ſhire, by Mr. <hi>Hardwick</hi> Chaplain to the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi>) uſurping the Cure, after Doctor <hi>Pask,</hi> Maſter of <hi>Clare</hi>-Hall, was outed and ſequeſtred; for the ſaid <hi>Hardwick,</hi> reading in the Church, for part of his own, or the Morning-Service, before Sermon, the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> having read to the laſt <hi>Verſe,</hi> which contained God's Promiſe of clothing the Enemies of his anointed with ſhame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he paſſed by the <hi>Verſe,</hi> and then went on.</p>
               <p>Which Mr. <hi>Hern</hi> there preſent obſerving, went out of the Church immediately; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his reſolution, upon <hi>Hardwick</hi>'s not owning one place of Scripture, as well as another, heard him no more, the time he lived in Town.</p>
               <p>And thus the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that have lived, and do live among us, through pretence of their New Light (which is the blackneſs of darkneſs here) their contrary Revelations to thoſe in the time of the Goſpel, and before, and through their falſe and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Expoſitions of holy Scripture, they have darkned the Heavens of God, and the light of his Grace ſo in this life, that they have done in this our Age, as our Saviour ſaid, the Scribes, Phariſees, and Hypocrites had done then, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. namely, ſhut up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven before men, neither going in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33732:58"/>themſelves, nor ſuffering many that would enter, to go in.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed Lord, in whoſe hands are the heads and hearts of all men, lighten the darkneſs of all their underſtandings, change and ſoften all their hearts, that they may recover their ſtrength, and ſtrengthen all them they have ſeduced, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they go hence, and be not ſeen.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>13th</hi> Conſideration, which is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether one end of Chriſt's coming into the World, was not to redeem men from the Rudiments and Traditions of men, of which this is one; And whether it be not againſt the Blood, and Spirit, and Goſpel of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.10, 11.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Opinion of the Author in this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be ſet forth in two Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>The firſt is this:</p>
               <p>One end of Chriſt's coming into the World, was to put an end to the Uſe and Obſervation of the Ruliments and Traditions of men, and to the Uſe of the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in the years 1500 and 1600, after his coming into the World, or going out of it. The latter part of the Propoſition is evidently a concluſion flowing from the Conſideration; for he ſaith that this Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> was one of the Rudiments or Traditions that Chriſt came to put an end to.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33732:58"/>
               <p>In anſwer to which Propoſition I ſay;</p>
               <p>The end of Chriſt's coming into the World, was to compleat the love and kindneſs of God to Mankind, which was the redemption and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of men, as is affirmed in the Firſt to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>This is a faithful ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners.</hi> And this he was to perform in two particulars:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In giving himſelf by the Paſſion of his whole Life and Death, a ranſom for all, 1 <hi>Tim. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> In teaching the World by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Apoſtles the way to true Faith, and due Obedience, in order to their Salvation, through the all-ſufficient Sacrifice of himſelf, offered upon the Altar of his Croſs, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>Acts</hi> the <hi>3d, verſ.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>Moſes ſaid unto the fathers, A prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you of your brethren, like unto me; him ſhall you hear in all things, whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you. And it ſhall come to paſs, that every ſoul which will not hear that prophet, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed from among the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in anſwer to the Author's Opinion in this firſt Propoſition, it would be conſidered, what Chriſt, this Prophet, and his Apoſtles have done in reſpect to this latter particular, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and Abolition of the Laws and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances were in uſe and obſervation at his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:33732:59"/>
               <p>The Laws before Chriſt's coming are by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines divided into Moral, Judicial, and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial. The Moral Law contained in the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> are <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> veritatis,</hi> of an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting truth. There was no end put to theſe by Chriſt, but were ratified by the Command and Obſervation of himſelf and his Apoſtles, <hi>Matthew</hi> the <hi>5th, verſ.</hi> 19. <hi>I am not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Law or the Prophets, but to fulfil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then there was the Judicial Laws, impoſed upon the <hi>Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> by way of Penalties, and other ways; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Upon the breach of ſome Moral Laws, as ſtoning to death, upon committing Adultery, and reſtoring things ſtolen four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Upon the breach of ſome Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial or Typical Laws, as the ſtoning to death the man for gathering ſticks upon the ſabbath day, <hi>Nam.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>verſ.</hi> 32, 33. and cutting off thoſe that ſhould cat Leaven ſeven days before the Paſſover, and ſuch like. All which Judicial, and alſo all Ceremonial Laws, and Typical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurations of Chriſt were ended by our Saviour's coming, Doctrine and Death, as is evident, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>blotting out the hand-writing of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which was againſt us, which was contrary to us: nailing it to his croſs.</hi> Yea, I ſay, they were all ended by him, together with ſeveral of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Feſtivals, which the Apoſtle calls Rudiments, or weak and beggarly Elements, as is to be ſeen, <hi>Galat.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Ye obſerve
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33732:59"/>days, and months, and times, and years, I am afraid of ye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now it remains that I anſwer to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words next laid down indefinitely, <hi>and Traditions of men,</hi> which muſt not be granted in its latitude.</p>
               <p>By Tradition is underſtood for nothing taught by word or writing, for mens obſervation; of which Traditions ſome are aboliſhed, and others may, or muſt be continued. There were ſome Traditions, beſides Rudiments and Ordinances before ſpoken of, that our Savi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r condemned; one was the Command of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ers, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waſhing of hands before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Duty to be performed before: this our Saviour condemned, <hi>Matt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2, 3.</p>
               <p>And there he condemned ſeveral Traditions of the Scribes and Phariſees, which made the Laws of God of none effect.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, (Notwithſtanding Chriſt's co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and putting an end to ſuperſtitious, and wicked Traditions, as before mentioned,) There are ſome Traditions muſt, and others may, and ought to be kept; ſome muſt be kept, namely, ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of in the <hi>2d</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians, chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. where he ſaith, <hi>Hold faſt the traditions which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have been taught, whether by word, or our epiſtle.</hi> Theſe were the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Directions of the Apoſtles, in order to juſtifying Faith, and a right worſhipping and ſerving of God, and were of Divine Authority, and to be obſerved.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33732:60"/>
               <p>And ſecondly, there were and are Traditions, though not of the ſame abſolute neceſſity with the former, yet that may lawfully, and ought to be obſerved. Of this ſort are the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Exhortations, and Reprehenſions of the Miniſters of the Word, appointed and ordained (by them in Authority) to ſeed that part of the Flock of Chriſt they be ſet over.</p>
               <p>Alſo of this ſort of Traditions, are all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, Canons, Liturgies, Ceremonies; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided firſt, that they be either according to the Word of God, or not againſt it.</p>
               <p>And provided ſecondly, that the end of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them be good, that is, not to make them eſſential parts of God's Worſhip, as if God's Worſhip and way of Salvation were not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated as to the <hi>Eſſe,</hi> being, or ſubſtantials of it by himſelf, without them. As alſo, that the end of thoſe things injoyned be but <hi>pro bene, velmelius eſſe,</hi> for the well or better being of our Worſhip, in order to obtaining God's Favour and Mercy; as alſo that we might tread the ſteps of the true Worſhippers of God in our lawful Forms of Prayer, joyning together, and uniting one with another in a more powerful and prevailing way with our God than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, according to the Exhortations of <hi>David</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> being for the forementioned end; that of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 34. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>O,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>magniſie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together.</hi> And the Prayer of St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:33732:60"/>for the <hi>Romans</hi> and all believers to be like mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is for this very end and purpoſe, <hi>Romans</hi> the <hi>15th, verſ.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>Now the God of all patience and conſolation, gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ye to be like minded ene to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, that ye may with one mind, and one mouth glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now how ſhall the Author make out the truth of what remains in the Propoſition, which is the point even only intended by him herein; namely, that the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in the Propoſition, was one of thoſe Rudiments, or Traditions, which Chriſt came to put an end to. I think I have mentioned in my Anſwer to this Propoſition, moſt part of the Rudiments and Traditions that Chriſt ended and aboliſhed at his coming into this World, and at his death, and I cannot but judge it a great piece of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the Author to ſay, that Chriſt came to end that Liturgy which was not in being till above 1400 years after his coming.</p>
               <p>Well, but perhaps the Adverſaries will ſay, things that come to paſs at any time have a being in the fore-ſight and fore-knowledge of God, before they have their actual being in the World, as it was ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Revelations</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. That he was the Lamb ſlain before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World.</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Chriſt, the Son of God, was not the Lamb
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33732:61"/>ſlain, only from the foundation of the World, in the ſacrifice of the godly, as in a type of him, but was alſo ſaid to be ſlain, in reſpect to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight and deſign of God the Father, who of his everlaſting love, gave him a ranſom for Mankind by his death. And indeed to foreſee and foretell things before they happen, or come to paſs, is peculiar and proper only unto God, as is evident <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 41. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22, 23. And therefore in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect I can grant, that the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book had a being at or before Chriſt's coming. But how can the Author make appear, that either Chriſt or his Spirit have diſallowed of it? As for our Saviour, he was ſo far from being againſt well compoſed Liturgies, and conſequently of being againſt ours (becauſe as King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, the bleſſed Martyr, ſaid upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance againſt the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, in his ſeventh Paragraph, that he held this to be a well compoſed one) that indeed Chriſt compoſed a Liturgy himſelf, to be uſed by all that ſhould be his Diſciples, as <hi>Luke</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. which Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy or Prayer of our Saviour (as the aforeſaid Martyr ſaid in the Tenth Paragraph of thoſe Obſervations) was the Warrant and original Pattern of all ſet Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church. And I ſay eſpecially of ours (the Author ſo much inveighs againſt) becauſe if it be not the beſt that ever was extant before it, yet it was a Liturgy inferiour to none.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33732:61"/>
               <p>So that for a bleſſed return and compliance of Diſſenters to an Union with our Church, I ſhall exhort all that ſhall peruſe this ſmall Tractate, to conſider diligently as to the Anſwers here to the ſeveral Errors couched in theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo alſo diligently to ponder the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philippians, chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind. Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, but in lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond Propoſition in the <hi>13th</hi> Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Book of</hi> Common-Prayer <hi>is againſt the Blood and Spirit and Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> For proof whereof, he alledgeth 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Sure this man hath eaten ſhame (as in the Proverb) and digeſted it, that he dare charge ſuch apparent untruths upon our Church, which is as full for Chriſt, his Spirit, and Goſpel, as any of the Churches in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> I appeal to any man that hath peruſed the Liturgy and Doctrine of our Church for the truth hereof, for condemnation of this preſent Error.</p>
               <p>Our Church, in our <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book, owns Chriſt the only Mediator of Redemption, by the Merits of his active and paſſive Obedience, according to that in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18, 19,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33732:62"/>
                  <hi>Ye were not redeemed with corruptible things,</hi> &amp;c <hi>but with the precious blood.</hi> For every where our Liturgy owns with the Apoſtle there, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are redeemed with the precious blood of Chriſt And for evidence hereof, conſider the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of our Prayers, and Collects therein and they ſhall ſee all begged there of God for the ſake, merits, or worthineſs of Jeſus Chriſt And if any man do but conſider the Communion. Service, and that of the Sacrament of Baptiſm, he muſt be wilfully, if not maliciouſly blind, to ſay, that our Church or Liturgy is againſt the blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Further, For evidence of the Author's falſe charge here, let men conſider what Bleſſings and Thankſgivings we do annually offer to God for his giving his Son to us, our all-ſufficient Saviour and Redeemer, in the joyful Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morations of his Birth, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We own him the only Mediator of Interceſſion in Heaven, and thereby to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the Father the ſending of the Holy Ghoſt upon the Diſciples in the day of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt; And that daily, through his Interceſſion, he ſends the Holy Ghoſt into our hearts, to ſanctifie us, to lead us into all truths, guiding us thereby into the way of Peace and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>How are we then againſt the Blood, or Spirit, or Goſpel of Chriſt? If our Adverſaries will peruſe that Service-Book, and the Doctrine of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33732:62"/>our Church, contained in the 39 Articles, and the Homilies, they ſhall find all things therein agreeing with the Goſpel, and the Writings of the Holy Ghoſt, deliver'd by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, and his other Penmen.</p>
               <p>So that to conclude my Anſwer, as to what is objected againſt the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book of our Church, in this <hi>13th</hi> Conſideration, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, I cannot think but that if St. <hi>Paul</hi> were now upon earth, taking the care of all the Churches, as before he did, he would give the like approbation of our Church both for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Diſcipline, as he did of the <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Church, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. where he ſaith, <hi>He was with them in Spirit, joying, and beholding their Order, and ſtedfaſtneſs of their Faith in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>14th</hi> Conſideration, which is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether at the great and terrible day of Judgment, any Magiſtrates, Miniſters, or People can juſtifie before Chriſt, the Making, Impoſing, Reading, or Hearing of this, or the like Service?</q>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer affirmative, They all may juſtifie their ſo doing before Chriſt, as hath been evidenced in the Anſwers to the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in what hath been laid down before for juſtification of ſet Forms, as before limited in theſe Papers.</p>
               <p>But then further, In this <hi>14th</hi> Conſideration the Author would have men conſider, Whether
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33732:63"/>good men, as far as they build with this material (namely, <hi>by worſhipping of God by this Book of Common-Prayer</hi>) will not at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuffer loſs.</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Having conſider'd of this <hi>Quaere,</hi> and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of building upon Chriſt the foundation of our hope by way of worſhipping and ſerving God by way of Prayer and Thankſgiving (as in our bounden duty to do) and performing the ſaid duty according to the Form of our <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> Book: I ſee not how the Builders, that build with this Material, devoutly and fervently in ſpirit, can ſuffer loſs thereby, that is, loſe their labour in ſo calling upon God. For further evidence whereof, I refer the Readers to my Obſervation of the great benefit King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of moſt bleſſed memory, and divers there mentioned, yea and the whole Kingdom have reaped thereby, in my foregoing Diſcourſe upon the the <hi>6th</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p>But laſt of all he puts the <hi>Quaere,</hi> 
                  <q>Whether thoſe can ſtand then in the Judgment, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear, ſhame, and ſorrow, that have caſt out, perſecuted, impriſoned, or otherwiſe afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the true Preachers and Servants of God, who did chuſe to obey God rather than men, and to obeſerve his Divine Will rather than mens Traditions.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer,</p>
               <p>That if by the true Preachers and Servants
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33732:63"/>of God, he underſtand the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> to our Church before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rebellion; or if he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by means the rebellion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Army, and their Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains; then his Argument <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alls to the ground, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then he argues, <hi>ex non ſuppoſins, &amp; ex non ſupponendis,</hi> of things not granted, not to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for that they were neither true Preachers, nor true Servants of God; for evidence whereof, I refer the Reader to my Diſcourſe upon the firſt Propoſition, deducible out of this Author's <hi>7th</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p>And for further Anſwer to this <hi>Quaere,</hi> what the Author propoſeth to the World to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd of, I wiſh earneſtly might be laid to heart, of all them that are alive of the late Rebellion, for their true and unfeigned repentance, that they might obtain at God's hand forgiveneſs of their ſins, that are as red as Crimſon, in Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting, Impriſoning, Impoveriſhing, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, and otherwiſe afflicting King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of moſt bleſſed memory, the careful and godly Hierarchy of our Church, the true Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God's Word, and others the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants of the Almighty, who did chuſe rather to obey God, and to obſerve his Divine Will, rather than the Fanatical Inventions and Traditions of a rebellious multitude.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
